<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title level="m" type="main">Extracts from Gauntt</title>
            <!-- this whole header needs to be updated because what I'm transcribing here are
            extracts from Gauntt's actual narrative written aboard the Macedonian-->
            <author>Charles Gauntt</author>
            <editor>Mary Isbell</editor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcription, encoding, and notes</resp>
               <name xml:id="initials">Mary Isbell</name>
               <!-- I notice forme work in this journal (the year is along the right side of the page and
                  the month and day is that the top right of the page. He includes the first part of the word to start the next page at the bottom of
                  the page on a new line. He uses superscript to write "o'clock," which I may not care to reproduce. The underlinings for rend as is I
                  do want to preserve...-->
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>2019</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>?????</publisher>
            <date>2019</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International License. </p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <monogr>
                  <author>Charles Gauntt</author>
                  <title>Private record of Charles Gauntt, commander in the Navy of the United States</title>
                  <idno type="callno">Edition created from copy held at the Natinal Archives [call number info]</idno>
                  <imprint>
                     <date>????</date>
                     <biblScope>
                        <!-- type="pubPlace" -->
                        <ref type="address">Philadelphia</ref>
                        <name type="publisher">Privately Printed</name>
                     </biblScope>
                     <note type="project">?????</note>
                  </imprint>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <particDesc>
            <listPerson>
               <person xml:id="Franey">
                  <note>What can we know about Franey other than "(steerage servant) a veteran"<bibl>
                        <author><persName>Lessig, Lawrence</persName></author>. <title>Free Culture</title>: <title type="sub">How Big Media Uses
                           Technology and the Law to Lock Down Culture and Control Creativity</title>. <publisher>The Penguin Press</publisher>,
                           <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>; <date when="2004"/>. <idno type="ISBN">1-59420-006-8</idno>
                     </bibl></note>
               </person>
               <person xml:id="Williams_carpenter">
                  <note>What can we know about Williams other than that he played Variella?<bibl>
                        <author><persName>Lessig, Lawrence</persName></author>. <title>Free Culture</title>: <title type="sub">How Big Media Uses
                           Technology and the Law to Lock Down Culture and Control Creativity</title>. <publisher>The Penguin Press</publisher>,
                           <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>; <date when="2004"/>. <idno type="ISBN">1-59420-006-8</idno>
                     </bibl></note>
               </person>
               <person xml:id="Bunnell">
                  <note>We know many things about Bunnell. page 8 of 48 in pdf of macedonian musters...says some things that are a bit illegible<bibl>
                        <author><persName>Lessig, Lawrence</persName></author>. <title>Free Culture</title>: <title type="sub">How Big Media Uses
                           Technology and the Law to Lock Down Culture and Control Creativity</title>. <publisher>The Penguin Press</publisher>,
                           <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>; <date when="2004"/>. <idno type="ISBN">1-59420-006-8</idno>
                     </bibl></note>
               </person>
               <person xml:id="Williams_Sneer">
                  <note>Also perhaps of the foretop? perhaps 9 of 48 in musters document (could also be the John Williams on page 11 of 48 also could
                     be thomas williams, also on the same page (11 of 48)?<bibl>
                        <author><persName>Lessig, Lawrence</persName></author>. <title>Free Culture</title>: <title type="sub">How Big Media Uses
                           Technology and the Law to Lock Down Culture and Control Creativity</title>. <publisher>The Penguin Press</publisher>,
                           <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>; <date when="2004"/>. <idno type="ISBN">1-59420-006-8</idno>
                     </bibl></note>
               </person>
               <person xml:id="Fanigan">
                  <note>Worked on scenery...possibly John Fanigan page 7 of 48 in pdf of macedonian musters<bibl>
                        <author><persName>Lessig, Lawrence</persName></author>. <title>Free Culture</title>: <title type="sub">How Big Media Uses
                           Technology and the Law to Lock Down Culture and Control Creativity</title>. <publisher>The Penguin Press</publisher>,
                           <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>; <date when="2004"/>. <idno type="ISBN">1-59420-006-8</idno>
                     </bibl></note>
               </person>
               <person xml:id="Horton">
                  <note>of the foretop, played Briefwit<bibl>
                        <author><persName>Lessig, Lawrence</persName></author>. <title>Free Culture</title>: <title type="sub">How Big Media Uses
                           Technology and the Law to Lock Down Culture and Control Creativity</title>. <publisher>The Penguin Press</publisher>,
                           <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>; <date when="2004"/>. <idno type="ISBN">1-59420-006-8</idno>
                     </bibl></note>
               </person>
            </listPerson>
            <listOrg>
               <org xml:id="Macedonian">
                  <note>What can we know about Macedonian</note>
               </org>
               <org xml:id="Congress">
                  <note>What can we know about Congress</note>
               </org>
            </listOrg>
         </particDesc>
      </profileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>format of book retained; not much else to say</p>
         </editorialDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>

         <pb n="15"/>
         <div>
            <head>20th</head>
            <p>Much rain during the 24 hours the crew employed washing their clothes. <!--  Lat. Ob 30. 11.S Long: by d:r. 42.44'W. Thermo: 74-->
               Written hand bills were distributed about the ship this afternoon, giving notice that a play called the "Weather Cock," with an after
               piece <hi rend="underline">entitled</hi> the Sailor's Fortune, would be performed in the evening. The <choice>
                  <orig>author</orig>
                  <corr/>
               </choice><pb n="16"/>Authorship of the latter piece, is claimed by David C. Bunnel, Carpenter's Yeoman of the Macedonian, who, having
               previously obtained permission of our Commander, and assisted by a few of his shipmates, had got up the aforenamed pieces for the
               treble purpose of, in the first place, giving amusement to the Officers &amp; crew of the ship, Secondly, <add>of</add>his <hi
                  rend="underline">faculties</hi> or <hi rend="underline">powers</hi> of the mind, as an Author, and Thirdly, to show his <hi
                  rend="underline">merit</hi> as an Actor, in all of which, except the former, he failed most egregiously. Every necessary preparation
               being made, the Curtain rose at 7 <hi rend="superscript">o</hi>Clock, when the Play was commenced, <hi rend="underline">middled</hi>
               and ended, so was the Farce, and, to say a great deal in a few words, the Audiences were treated with the combined talent of the <hi
                  rend="underline">Crew</hi> of the Macedonian, the Officers laughed heartily, and were much amused with the novelty of the scene.
               every encouragement, consistent with the discipline of the Ship, will be given towards promoting this species of amuseument; it has, I
               think, a tendency to create contentment among the crew, which is of some consideration, when it is known, that we are bound on a cruise
               of three years.</p>
            <p>[details about weather on intervening days 26th, 27th, 28th<pb n="17"/></p>
         </div>
         <div>
            <head>29th</head>
            <p>Commences with moderate winds &amp; pleasant, at 3 made sail, found the sea, considerably discolored. Sounded with 60 fathoms of line
               no bottom
               <!-- I'm not including all of the underlinings, but there are some--><!-- Lat: Ob: 35. 59'S. Long: d.r. 50
                  03' W Co: S 35 W.-->The
               crew employed this day in getting below all the heavy articles, bot from the tops and spar deck, such as kedge anchors, round shot,
               grape &amp; canister, spare spars, arm chests, &amp; this preparation was considered necessary before the ship reached, the formidable,
               Cape Horn, so represented by some navigators.</p>
         </div>
         <div>
            <head>Dec: 30</head>
            <p>Lat. Ob: 37 44; South Long: by d.r. 51 31' w. Co: S.S'NW Long: by Lunar Ob: 50. 41' 45" W.</p>
         </div>
         <div>
            <head>Dec: 31st.</head>
            <p>Set steering sails. Weather pleasant at 1/2 past 12 oClock a.m. discovered a light bearing N.E. ends fresh winds &amp; cloudy.
               Latitutde Ob: 39. 00' South. Long: by d.r. 53. 35' W. Long: by Lunar Ob: 52 42' 30: W. Thermor: 62. 30'</p>
         </div>
         <div>
            <head>January 1st</head>
            <p>The New Year commenced with fresh winds from the N.W. Set steering sails. At 3h 30m p.m. carried away the main top gallant mast near
               the Cap. Took in steering sails &amp; stay sails. Sent down top gallant yards &amp; top gallant masts. got up <hi rend="underline"
                  >stump</hi> top gallt masts top gallt yards &amp; set top gallant sails. rigged in flying jib boom &amp; set steering sails at
               meridian. Ends clear &amp; pleasant. Lat: Ob: 40. 57' S. Long: by d.r. 54. 25' W. by L. O. 53. 50' w. Thermometer 62. 30'</p>
         </div>
         <div>
            <head>2d</head>
            <p>took in steering sails. lowered the quarter boat to try the Current &amp; found it setting 1/4 of a mile per hour West. Lat: ob: 42.
               30;S. Long: d.r. 55. 43; W. therm: 62. 30; Course S. by W 1/2 W.<pb n="18"/></p>
         </div>
         <div type="entry">
            <head>3d</head>
            <p>On New Years evening the Play of the "Weathercock" was again performed, with the afterpiece called the "Cob<add>b</add>ler &amp; his
               daughter," with songs &amp; the whole got up and the farce written, by our indefatigable <hi rend="underline">author</hi> &amp; <hi
                  rend="underline">actor</hi> David C. Bunnel (carpenter's Yeoman) for the information of those who may chance to read these remarks,
               as well as to please my own fancy, I herein copy from the "Thespian Critic and Theatrical Review"' (a paper edited &amp; written on
               board) the following criticism of the play above mentioned.</p>
            <div source="Thespian_Critic" type="quotation">
               <head><hi rend="underline">Theatrical_January 2d 1819.</hi></head>
               <p>The Thespian Theatre was opened last evening for the second time with the following entertainment of the Weathercock and the
                     Cob<add>b</add>ler &amp; his Daughter. Tristram by <persName ref="#Bunnell">Mr D.G.B.</persName> from the Theatre Royal. As
                  expectation is always on tiptoe at the debut of a new performer, &amp; his merits or demerits occasion much animadversion, we have
                  taken the troubel of minutely observing this new Performer's commencement to give our friends an impartial account of him; and we
                  must say, that our expectations were much disappointed, particularly so with regard to his tautology &amp; his gesticulation. In act
                  1st Scene 1st for saying did You never hear of Demosthenes the Athenian Orator &amp;c he repeats "did you never hear of De_mo_thens
                  the A_the_an orator_certainly the most vulgar pronunciation_In his next speech of_"I think I see him now awaking"_his gesticulations
                  were so violent that it reminded us of a frantic Bedlamite, and seemed [unreadable] with the idea that the more noise there was, the
                  more admir<choice>
                     <orig>able</orig>
                     <corr/>
                  </choice><pb n="19"/>able his performance._again he says_one soul "a_ni_ha_mates &amp;c for animates_where he picked this jargon, or
                  whether in his deep researches after literature, he conceives he has found a more correct manner of pronunciation than his
                  cotemporaries_Johnson or Walker, we must leave the Public to judge_again while conversing with Sneer (<persName
                     ref="#Williams_Sneer"><hi rend="underline">Mr</hi> Williams</persName>) to personate Juliet, in saying Oh that I were a glove
                  upon that hand &amp;c his grimace is so intolerable that it was painful to observe him and he either forgot or was ignorant that in
                  addressing Juliet, he ought to have bended one knee_but no, he stood half bent, with one arm extended, &amp; the other with his
                  finger pointed as if to command silence of his Juliet that she may hear his rhapsody. _But of all the canting noisey Billingsgate
                  slang, his speech of A soldier, a General &amp;c &amp;c is made to represent it to a hair._His eyes roll, his chest is extended, his
                  limbs compressed into the form of a letter S and he makes the whole house tremble while he wars it out_and at intervals, bellowing
                  like a child crying for a piece of bread and butter; but when he takes his sword_then_then comes the tug of war, and he fancies that
                  admiration sits on every countenance, and he dances from one end of the stage to the other like a dancing Bear._Again_ in the scene
                  between Tristram &amp; the Gardener,_for vile Habiliments he repeats_Vile Ha_bit_a_ments. What he meant no one could form an idea,
                  unless it was by the action of throwing off <choice>
                     <orig>his</orig>
                     <corr/>
                  </choice><pb n="20"/>his clothes._but enough for the present, we could point out a number of other material instances of defect; but
                  hope that these will suffuse into him a wish to correct his manners and pronunciation_</p>
               <p>Old Fickle by <del>M</del>
                  <persName ref="#franey">Franey</persName>, (steerage servant) a veteran_ on the whole, we were much entertained by him &amp; the
                  performance of the character, <del>pretty well</del> &amp; though we hope, he will be rather less forgetful on another night; and we
                  sincerely believe, that he will be a valuable acquisition to our Theatre_</p>
               <p>Miss Variella, by <persName ref="#Williams_carpenter">Williams</persName> (of the Carpenters crew) "grace in all <hi
                     rend="underline">her</hi> steps, Heaven in her eye, In every gesture, dignity and love."_</p>
               <p>Briefwit, <persName ref="#Horton"><hi rend="underline">Mr</hi> H.</persName>
                  <del>as</del>a stiff <del>a</del> piece of machinery &amp; greater than the author intended I dare say, for he was both Briefwit and
                  Briefless. Sneer, <persName ref="#Williams_Sneer"><hi rend="underline">Mr</hi> Williams</persName>, with a little improvement will
                  do well in the characters_ The piece went off without either many marks of approbation or disapprobation, and we hope, that the
                  piece will not be resumed without some attention being paid to the errors &amp; defects pointed out.</p>
               <p>The Pantomime was so wretchedly performed, that even the name of it would have been incomprehensible, unless we had seen it in the
                  Play Bills_</p>
               <p>The songs were, however, very well, but the subject of some were too pointed, tho we believe unintentionally so by the Author._ We
                  were glad to see a full house on the commencement, as without that, the expense could not <choice>
                     <orig>be</orig>
                     <corr/>
                  </choice><pb n="21"/> be continued,_We saw the side Boxes were filled wtih the Naval Heroes_some of distinction &amp; rank_ We have
                  been thus particular with the faults of <persName ref="#Bunnell"><hi rend="underline">Mr</hi> D.C.B.</persName> not with the wish to
                  dihearten him, but to lead him to improvement, that he may thereby reap the reward of his exertion &amp; talents &amp; we sincerely
                  hope he may_"</p>
            </div>
            <div type="account">
               <p> About this time, an opposition Paper appeared, called the "Macedonian Scourge," The following remarks are taken from Paper No.
                  7_</p>
            </div>
            <div type="quotation" source="Macedonian_Scourge">
               <div type="Editorial">
                  <head><hi rend="underline">_Editorial_</hi></head>
                  <p>"The Editor of this paper is really sorry that the remarks contained in his paper of January the third, should have been of such
                     a nature as to draw forth the "Ire" of the gentleman who heads the Thespian Band, That a gentleman of his qualifications should
                     have recourse to caricature for the purpose of defaming him (who would be the last to injure the Thespian Throng,) is really
                     astonishing_ With pleasure do we appeal to an enlightened Public for an opinion of the following, which was made with no other
                     view than to maintain the dignity of the stage, and that lustre which spreads it refulgent beams around the personage of this
                     Modern Othello."_</p>
               </div>
               <div type="article">
                  <head>
                     <hi rend="underline">"Theatrical Entertainment Jany 2d 1819"</hi></head>
                  <p>Last Evening the crew of the Macedonian frigate were politely favoured with a rich repast of Theatrical labour in the display of
                     the "Weathercock" and a Pantomime of the Cobbler &amp; his Daughter_ We hope our Subscribers will excuse us for a digression from
                     our accustomed mode of issuing this paper in noticing the "Dramatis Personae" of those celebrated pieces,_Tristram,that most <choice>
                        <orig>imp</orig>
                        <corr/>
                     </choice><pb n="22"/>important part of the Weathercock, was assigned to the <hi rend="underline">Natural</hi> and <hi
                        rend="underline">acquired</hi>abilities of <persName ref="#Bunnell"><hi rend="underline">Mr</hi> David C. Bunnel</persName>,
                     who has for a length of time appeared, with so much honor to himself and advantage to the community, upon the Theatre of the
                     Congress and Macedonian Frigates. He is not however, without his imperfections, and in reminding him of them, we have not only
                     the reputation of the stage at heart, but that of his own welfare on this stage, and that to which he may be translated. In that
                     part which relates to his having arrived to the acme of perfection in the study of the Law, and the learned speech which he makes
                     to prove that he possesses that fund of knowledge, we discover that his pronunciation is totally incorrect, as he differs from
                     Johnson, Walker &amp; others, In pronouncing Demosthenes, he says Demosthenes, which must be disgusting to those who are familiar
                     with pointing and diction</p>
                  <p>In another part he says the Ane_than instead ofthe Athenean Orator, We hope that he will make it his study to repair the damages
                     done to the King's English</p>
               </div>
            </div>
         </div>




      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
