<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title level="m" type="main">Extracts from Gauntt</title>
            <author>Charles Gauntt</author>
            <editor>Mary Isbell</editor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcription, encoding, and notes</resp>
               <name xml:id="initials">Mary Isbell</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>2018</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>?????</publisher>
            <date>2018</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International License. </p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <monogr>
                  <author>Charles Gauntt</author>
                  <author>Ireton Gauntt</author>
                  <author>Charles Stockton Gauntt</author>
                  <title>Private record of Charles Gauntt, commander in the Navy of the United States</title>
                  <idno type="callno">Edition created from copy held at the American Antiquarian MuseumR G272 Gaun P839</idno>
                  <imprint>
                     <date>1839</date>
                     <biblScope>
                        <!-- type="pubPlace" -->
                        <ref type="address">Philadelphia</ref>
                        <name type="publisher">Privately Printed</name>
                     </biblScope>
                     <note type="project">?????</note>
                  </imprint>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <particDesc>
            <listPerson>
               <person xml:id="A_D_McArthur">
                  <note>Alexander D. McArthur, a clerk, joined the Chesapeake on December 9th 1857. He was born on December 25th 1835 in Woolwich,
                     Kent, making him 21 when he came aboard. Census records for the town of Woolwich in 1851 reveal the family of John McAurthur, a
                     captain in the Royal Marines, who lived with his wife Mary E., a son James (a gentleman, aged 29), a son John (no occupation,
                     aged 27), a son Henry (a clerk in the wine trade, aged 17), a son Alexander D (a scholar, aged 15), a son Hanibal (no occupation,
                     aged 13), and a servant Esther Johnson (aged 20).</note>
                  <!--<bibl><<msIdentifier><msName>Muster Book of Her Majesty's Ship Chesapeake Commencing 1st January 1858 Ending 31st March 1858</msName>
                        <institution>National Archives at Kew</institution>
                     <idno>ADM 38/2884</idno>
                     </msIdentifier></bibl>
                  <bibl>
                  <bibl><msIdentifier><msName>Census Returns of England and Wales, 1851. Kew, Surrey, England</msName><institution>The National Archives of the
                     UK (TNA): Public Record Office (PRO)</institution>                       
                     </msIdentifier></bibl>-->
               </person>
               <person>
                  <persName xml:id="J_W_L_Bampfield">John William Lewis Bampfield</persName>
                  <note>Reverend John William Lewis Bampfield joined the Chesapeake on July 24th 1857 and was a regular contributor to and supporter
                     of The Young Idea. While his age is not recorded in the muster book, census records reveal that Bampfield was born in June of
                     1823, so he was in his mid-thirties during the cruise. He was commissioned as chaplain aboard a different royal naval vessel in
                     Port Royal, Jamaica before his arrival aboard the Chesapeake. His detailed journal provides an additional witness to The Young
                     Idea, providing fascinating points of contrast from the facsimile edition that McArthur had printed in 1867 and offering hints
                     about the authorship of contributions through his inclusion of the initials of authors (a marked list). </note>
               </person>
               <person>
                  <persName xml:id="Edgell">Harry Edmund Edgell</persName>
                  <note>Harry Edmund Edgell joined the Chesapeake as Commodore after the period chronicled in the issues included in this edition. He
                     was an enthusiastic supporter of The Young Idea. In <hi rend="italics">Martello Tower" in China, and the Pacific in H.M.S.
                        "Tribune," 1856-60</hi>, Francis Martin Norman recounts Edgell's enthusiastic support for a shipboard theatrical aboard H.M.S.
                     Tribune in 1857, when he was captain of the ship. Edgell composed the prologue for the play and painted the drop-scene (50). The
                     National Maritime Museum at Greenwich (NMM) holds over 300 watercolors by Edgell, including some undertaken during the cruise
                     chronicled in The Young Idea. The NMM's biographical note on Edgell reads as follows: "Edgell was promoted to lieutenant in 1828,
                     to commander in 1837 and to captain in 1846. He was appointed to command the Tribune in 1855 when she was in the Crimea. During
                     this commission she went to the Pacific and finally to China. In 1857 Edgell was the Senior Naval Officer at Hong Kong and he
                     transferred into the Bittern tender commanding the gun boats on the Canton River during the hostilities with the Chinese. In 1858
                     be was given command of the squadron in Indian waters, during which time he commanded the Chesapeake and later the Retribution.
                     The latter returned to England and was paid off in 1860. Edgell had no further active employment and was promoted on the retired
                     list, reaching the rank of vice-admiral in 1871."</note>
               </person>
               <person>
                  <persName xml:id="Watson">Commodore Rundle Burges Watson</persName>
                  <note>Excerpts from “Watson, Rundle Burges” by <bibl><author>by J.K. Laughton, rev. Andrew Lambert</author></bibl> for the
                           <bibl><title>Oxford Dictionary of National Biography</title></bibl>: <quote>"Watson, Rundle Burges (1809–1860), naval
                        officer, was the eldest son of Captain Joshua Rowley Watson (1772–1810). He entered the navy in November 1821, and was
                        promoted lieutenant on 7 October 1829. [...] On 23 December 1842 he was advanced to post rank, and on 24 December was made a
                        CB. [...] In December 1852 [Watson] was appointed to the new steam frigate Impérieuse (50 guns), then, and for some years
                        later, considered one of the finest ships in the navy. In 1854 she was sent into the Baltic in advance of the fleet, Watson
                        being senior officer of the squadron of small vessels appointed to watch the breaking up of the ice, and to see that no
                        Russian warships got to sea. It was an arduous service well performed. The Impérieuse continued with the flying squadron in
                        the Baltic during the campaigns of 1854 and 1855, and until the signing of peace in March 1856. As the senior officer of the
                        frigate squadron, and generally on detached service, Watson demonstrated the highest standards of seamanship, judgement, and
                        leadership. After the peace the Impérieuse was sent to the North American station; she returned to England and was paid off
                        early in 1857. From May 1856 until his death Watson was naval aide-de-camp to the queen. In June 1859 he was appointed
                        captain-superintendent of Sheerness Dockyard, where he died on 5 July 1860. An officer of great ability, Watson was one of the
                        last great sailing-ship captains, and the first frigate captain of the steam era."</quote></note>
               </person>
               <person>
                  <persName xml:id="Pratt">Archdeacon Pratt</persName>
                  <note>Excerpt from “Pratt, John Henry” by <bibl><author>Anita McConnell</author></bibl> for the <bibl><title>Oxford Dictionary of
                           National Biography</title></bibl>: <quote>“Pratt, John Henry (bap. 1809, d. 1871), Church of England clergyman and
                        mathematician, was baptized on 30 June 1809 at St Mary Woolnoth, London, one of two sons of Josiah Pratt (1768–1844), Church
                        of England clergyman, and his wife, Elizabeth, formerly Jowett. He was educated at Oakham School, Rutland, and entered
                        Gonville and Caius College, Cambridge, in 1829, graduating BA in 1833 as third wrangler. He was elected to a fellowship, and
                        proceeded MA in 1836. After taking orders he was appointed through the influence of Daniel Wilson, bishop of Calcutta, a
                        chaplain of the East India Company in 1838. He became Wilson's domestic chaplain and in 1850 archdeacon of
                     Calcutta.”</quote></note>
               </person>
               <person>
                  <persName xml:id="George_Horner">George Horner</persName>
                  <note>George Horner, a bandsman, joined the Chesapeake on August 12, 1857. He was born in London in 1817. The muster book for the
                     Chesapeake claims to offer the first entry for George Horner, perhaps meaning this was his first time at sea.<bibl>Muster Book of
                        Her Majesty's Ship Chesapeake Commencing 1st January 1858 Ending 31st March 1858, held by the National Archives at Kew (ADM
                        38/2884)</bibl></note>
               </person>
               <person>
                  <persName xml:id="Charles_Stewart">Charles Stewart</persName>
                  <note>Charles Stewart, an ordinary seaman, joined the Chesapeake on May 23, 1857. He was born in London and served aboard HMS
                     Gladiator just before joining the Chesapeake. He was born in 1834.<bibl>Muster Book of Her Majesty's Ship Chesapeake Commencing
                        1st January 1858 Ending 31st March 1858, held by the National Archives at Kew (ADM 38/2884)</bibl></note>
               </person>
               <person>
                  <persName xml:id="Thomas_Walsh">Thomas Walsh</persName>
                  <note>Thomas Walsh, an ordinary seaman, joined the Chesapeake on August 15, 1857. He was born in London in 1834 and served aboard
                     HMS Cressy just before joining the Chesapeake.<bibl>Muster Book of Her Majesty's Ship Chesapeake Commencing 1st January 1858
                        Ending 31st March 1858, held by the National Archives at Kew (ADM 38/2884)</bibl></note>
               </person>
               <person>
                  <persName xml:id="Robert_Wilkinson">Robert Wilkinson</persName>
                  <note>Robert Wilkinson, a private in the Royal Marines, joined the Chesapeake on July 25th 1857. He was born in Sitchfield,
                        Staffordshire.<bibl>Muster Book of Her Majesty's Ship Chesapeake Commencing 1st January 1858 Ending 31st March 1858, held by
                        the National Archives at Kew (ADM 38/2884)</bibl></note>
               </person>
               <person>
                  <persName xml:id="Henry_Underhill">Henry Underhill</persName>
                  <note>muster#153, ordinary seaman from Alesford, 36 when coming aboard the Chesapeake<bibl>Muster Book of Her Majesty's Ship
                        Chesapeake Commencing 1st January 1858 Ending 31st March 1858, held by the National Archives at Kew (ADM 38/2884)</bibl>
                  </note>
               </person>
               <person>
                  <persName xml:id="John_Welsh">John Welsh</persName>
                  <note>John Welsh, an ordinary seaman, joined the Chesapeake on February 20, 1857. He was born in Mayo<bibl>Muster Book of Her
                        Majesty's Ship Chesapeake Commencing 1st January 1858 Ending 31st March 1858, held by the National Archives at Kew (ADM
                        38/2884)</bibl></note>
               </person>
               <person>
                  <persName xml:id="Henry_Montagu">Henry Montagu</persName>
                  <note>Henry Montagu, yeoman of signals, joined the Chesapeake on July 28, 1857 after serving aboard HMS President. He was born in
                     St. Hilliers, Jersey (the Channel Islands) in 1826, making him 32 at the time of the performance.<bibl>Muster Book of Her
                        Majesty's Ship Chesapeake Commencing 1st January 1858 Ending 31st March 1858, held by the National Archives at Kew (ADM
                        38/2884)</bibl></note>
               </person>
               <person>
                  <persName xml:id="Isaac_Wright">Isaac Wright</persName>
                  <note>Isaac Wright, an ordinary sailor 2nd class, joined the Chesapeake on September 4th 1857. Hew as born in Sunderland in 1835,
                     making him 23 at the time of the performance.<bibl>Muster Book of Her Majesty's Ship Chesapeake Commencing 1st January 1858
                        Ending 31st March 1858, held by the National Archives at Kew (ADM 38/2884)</bibl></note>
               </person>
               <person>
                  <persName xml:id="Henry_Hamilton">Henry Hamilton</persName>
                  <note>C. R. B. Hamilton (the only Hamilton in the musters) was a naval cadet who served aboard <orgName ref="Colossus">HMS
                        Colossus</orgName> before joining the Chesapeake on July 23, 1857. He was born in County Tyrone, Ireland in December of 1842,
                     making him 15 at the time the performance<bibl>Muster Book of Her Majesty's Ship Chesapeake Commencing 1st January 1858 Ending
                        31st March 1858, held by the National Archives at Kew (ADM 38/2884)</bibl></note>
               </person>
               <person>
                  <persName xml:id="James_Brown">James Browne</persName>
                  <note>James Brown, an ordinary seaman, joined the Chesapeake on July 23, 1857, after serving aboard <orgName ref="Cuckoo">HMS
                        Cuckoo</orgName> until February 3, 1857. He was born at Sheerness on the 17th of January 1829, making him 28 at the time of
                     the performance<bibl>Muster Book of Her Majesty's Ship Chesapeake Commencing 1st January 1858 Ending 31st March 1858, held by the
                        National Archives at Kew (ADM 38/2884)</bibl></note>
               </person>
               <person>
                  <persName xml:id="William_Connell">William T Connell</persName>
                  <note>William T. Connell, an ordinary seaman, joined the Chesapeake on July 31 1857, after serving aboard <orgName ref="Eurydice"
                        >HMS Eurydice</orgName> until 17 June 1857. He was born in London in 1835, making him 27 at the time of the
                        performance.<bibl>Muster Book of Her Majesty's Ship Chesapeake Commencing 1st January 1858 Ending 31st March 1858, held by the
                        National Archives at Kew (ADM 38/2884)</bibl></note>
               </person>
               <person>
                  <persName xml:id="Taylor">Edward Taylor</persName>
                  <note>Edward Taylor, Assistant Engineer 3rd class (a commissioned officer), joined the Chesapeake on July 25th 1857. His age was not
                     recorded in the muster book<bibl>Muster Book of Her Majesty's Ship Chesapeake Commencing 1st January 1858 Ending 31st March 1858,
                        held by the National Archives at Kew (ADM 38/2884)</bibl></note>
               </person>
               <person>
                  <persName xml:id="Brownrigg">Charles J. Brownrigg</persName>
                  <note>Charles J. Brownrigg, a mate (a commissioned officer), joined the Chesapeake on August 4th, 1857. His age was not recorded in
                     the muster book.<bibl>Muster Book of Her Majesty's Ship Chesapeake Commencing 1st January 1858 Ending 31st March 1858, held by
                        the National Archives at Kew (ADM 38/2884)</bibl></note>
               </person>
               <person>
                  <persName xml:id="Wilkinson">Wilkinson</persName>
                  <note>Mr. Wilkinson, a clerk (a subordinate officer), joined the Chesapeake on July 23rd 1857 after serving aboard HMS Majestic. He
                     was born in Suffolk in 1836, which would make him 22 at the time of the cricket match in Calcutta<bibl>Muster Book of Her
                        Majesty's Ship Chesapeake Commencing 1st January 1858 Ending 31st March 1858, held by the National Archives at Kew (ADM
                        38/2884)</bibl></note>
               </person>
               <person>
                  <persName xml:id="Shortt">John Shortt</persName>
                  <note>John Shortt, a subordinate officer, joined the Chesapeake on July 23rd 1857, after serving aboard HMS Euridice. He was born in
                     Bombay in 1838, making him 20 at the time of this cricket match in Calcutta.<bibl>Muster Book of Her Majesty's Ship Chesapeake
                        Commencing 1st January 1858 Ending 31st March 1858, held by the National Archives at Kew (ADM 38/2884)</bibl></note>
               </person>
               <person>
                  <persName xml:id="Reynolds">S. Reynolds</persName>
                  <note>S. Reynolds, an ordinary seaman, joined the Chesapeake on September 4th 1857. He was born in Landport (Portsmouth) in 1839,
                     making him 19 at the time of the cricket match in Calcutta.<bibl>Muster Book of Her Majesty's Ship Chesapeake Commencing 1st
                        January 1858 Ending 31st March 1858, held by the National Archives at Kew (ADM 38/2884)</bibl></note>
               </person>
               <person>
                  <persName xml:id="Theobald">C.B. Theobald</persName>
                  <note>C.B. Theobald, a naval cadet, joined the Chesapeake on July 24th 1857. He was born in Mark's Tey, Essex in 1843, making him 15
                     at the time of the cricket match in Calcutta.<bibl>Muster Book of Her Majesty's Ship Chesapeake Commencing 1st January 1858
                        Ending 31st March 1858, held by the National Archives at Kew (ADM 38/2884)</bibl></note>
               </person>
               <person>
                  <persName xml:id="Cooper">Cooper</persName>
                  <note>There are three different members of the ship's company with the last name Cooper. The only thing we can tell about the
                     "Cooper" referenced in the cricket match is that he was not a commissioned officer, but an ordinary seaman.<bibl>Muster Book of
                        Her Majesty's Ship Chesapeake Commencing 1st January 1858 Ending 31st March 1858, held by the National Archives at Kew (ADM
                        38/2884)</bibl></note>
               </person>
               <person>
                  <persName xml:id="Chute">Charles T. Chute</persName>
                  <note>Charles T. Chute, a subordinate officer, joined the Chesapeake on July 23rd 1857, after serving aboard Euridice. He was born
                     in London in 1841, making him 17 at the time of the cricket match in Calcutta.<bibl>Muster Book of Her Majesty's Ship Chesapeake
                        Commencing 1st January 1858 Ending 31st March 1858, held by the National Archives at Kew (ADM 38/2884)</bibl></note>
               </person>
               <person>
                  <persName xml:id="Bew">James Bew</persName>
                  <note>James Bew, an experienced seaman, joined the Chesapeake on August 1st 1857. He was born in 1833, making him 25 at the time of
                     the cricket match in Calcutta.<bibl>Muster Book of Her Majesty's Ship Chesapeake Commencing 1st January 1858 Ending 31st March
                        1858, held by the National Archives at Kew (ADM 38/2884)</bibl></note>
               </person>
               <person>
                  <persName xml:id="Oxley">C.L. Oxley</persName>
                  <note>C.L. Oxley, a midshipman, joined the Chesapeake on July 29th 1857. He was born in 1841, making him 17 at the time of the
                     cricket match in Calcutta.<bibl>Muster Book of Her Majesty's Ship Chesapeake Commencing 1st January 1858 Ending 31st March 1858,
                        held by the National Archives at Kew (ADM 38/2884)</bibl></note>
               </person>
               <person>
                  <persName xml:id="Behadoor">Rajah Behadoor</persName>
                  <note>Still searching for biographical details on Rajah Behadoor</note>
               </person>
               <person>
                  <persName xml:id="Hope">Hope</persName>
                  <note>Hope played for the "squadron's eleven" and does not appear in Chesapeak muster book, which means he likely belonged to
                     another ship in the squadron<bibl>Muster Book of Her Majesty's Ship Chesapeake Commencing 1st January 1858 Ending 31st March
                        1858, held by the National Archives at Kew (ADM 38/2884)</bibl></note>
               </person>
               <person>
                  <persName xml:id="Haswell">Haswell</persName>
                  <note>Haswell served aboard Himalaya until he was injured and replaced by Piers.<bibl>Muster Book of Her Majesty's Ship Chesapeake
                        Commencing 1st January 1858 Ending 31st March 1858, held by the National Archives at Kew (ADM 38/2884)</bibl></note>
               </person>
               <person>
                  <persName xml:id="Kelly">Lieutenant Edward Kelly</persName>
                  <note>Lieutenant Edward Kelly does not appear in the muster book of HMS Chesapeake. <bibl>Muster Book of Her Majesty's Ship
                        Chesapeake Commencing 1st January 1858 Ending 31st March 1858, held by the National Archives at Kew (ADM
                     38/2884)</bibl></note>
               </person>
               <person>
                  <persName xml:id="Parkin">George H. Parkin</persName>
                  <note>George H. Parkin was named acting commander of HMS Chesapeake on February 1st 1858 and came aboard on February 25th after
                     serving aboard Roebuck. <bibl>Muster Book of Her Majesty's Ship Chesapeake Commencing 1st January 1858 Ending 31st March 1858,
                        held by the National Archives at Kew (ADM 38/2884)</bibl></note>
               </person>
               <person>
                  <persName xml:id="Piers">S.B. Piers</persName>
                  <note>S.B. Piers, a commander, joined the Chesapeake on July 28th 1857. He was discharged on January 22nd 1858 to serve aboard HMS
                     Himalaya when vice Haswell was invalided.<bibl>Muster Book of Her Majesty's Ship Chesapeake Commencing 1st January 1858 Ending
                        31st March 1858, held by the National Archives at Kew (ADM 38/2884)</bibl></note>
               </person>
               <person>
                  <persName xml:id="Namik_Pacha">Namik Pacha</persName>
                  <note>cite one of the articles on the uprising</note>
               </person>
            </listPerson>
            <listOrg>
               <org xml:id="Pelorus">
                  <note>HMS Pelorus was a Royal Navy screw corvette with twenty-one guns in the Pearl class. She was launched on February 5, 1858 and
                     her masting and fitting-out was completed on September 10, 1857. She was 200 feet long, 40 feet 4 inches at the broadest point,
                     with a depth in the hold of 23 feet 11 inches. As Lyon and Winfield explain, "Corvette designs were rapidly enlarged over the
                     1860s, as the corvette began to take over the traditional role of policing the high seas. To this end they were all built as
                     steam auxiliaries, designed to cruise under sail" (207). HMS Pelorus was broken up for parts at Devonport on February 3, 1869.
                     David Lyon and Rif Winfield, The Sail &amp; Steam Navy List: All the Ships of the Royal Navy, 1815–1889 (London: Chatham
                     Publishing), 2004.</note>
               </org>
               <org>
                  <orgName xml:id="Roebuck">Roebuck</orgName>
                  <note>HMS Roebuck was a Royal Navy despatch vessel with 5 guns in the Intrepid class. She was launched on March 22, 1856 and her
                     masting and fitting-out was completed on August 25, 1857. She was 200 feet long, 179 feet 5 1/4 inches at the broadest point,
                     with a depth in the hold of 14 feet 6 inches. She was built for a company of 100 men. As Lyon and Winfield explain, "The outbreak
                     of the Russian War demonstrated the need for numerous manoeuvrable, shallow-draught vessels for coastal and inshore operations in
                     the Baltic and Black Seas. Six small screw steamers of the Arrow Class were approved to be built by contract in the Thames [...]"
                     (218). The Roebuck was one of twenty additional vessels ordered in 1855 (218-219). David Lyon and Rif Winfield, The Sail &amp;
                     Steam Navy List: All the Ships of the Royal Navy, 1815–1889 (London: Chatham Publishing), 2004.</note>
               </org>
               <org>
                  <orgName xml:id="Cyclops">Cyclops</orgName>
                  <note>HMS Cyclops was a Royal Navy steam vessel with six guns in the Cyclops class. She was launched on July 10, 1839. She was 190
                     feet 3 inches long, 163 feet 6 inches at the broadest point, with a depth in the hold of 37 feet 6 inches. She was built for a
                     company of 175 to 200 men. As Lyon and Winfield explain, the ship was re-armed in 1856 "with 2x 68 pdrds (95cwt) on the pivots
                     and 4 x 10in (84cwt) on the broadside trucks." They also explain that she "was fitted 1856/57 to assist with the laying of the
                     Atlantic cable (151). David Lyon and Rif Winfield, The Sail &amp; Steam Navy List: All the Ships of the Royal Navy, 1815–1889
                     (London: Chatham Publishing), 2004. </note>
               </org>
               <org>
                  <orgName xml:id="Chesapeake">Chesapeake</orgName>
                  <note>HMS Chesapeake was a Royal Navy screw frigate with fifty-one guns in the Forte (or Imperieuse) class, which was one of several
                     classes including the thirty new wooden screw frigates completed between 1849 and 1865 (197). She was built in dry dock, launched
                     on September 7, 1855, and her masting and fitting-out was completed on August 28, 1857. She was 212 feet long, 50 feet 2 inches
                     at the broadest point, with a depth in the hold of 16 feet and 9 inches. She was built for a company of 515 men. The Chesapeake
                     was sold in 1867 to be broken up for parts at Charlton (200). David Lyon and Rif Winfield, The Sail &amp; Steam Navy List: All
                     the Ships of the Royal Navy, 1815–1889 (London: Chatham Publishing), 2004.</note>
               </org>
            </listOrg>
         </particDesc>
      </profileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>format of book retained; not much else to say</p>
         </editorialDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>

         <pb n="19"/>
         <div>
            <p>...</p>
            <p>I again visited Washington, and was ordered, July 10th. 1818, to join my old ship the Macedonian I proceeded to the Navy Yard
               Charleston, Massachusetts, where the ship lay fitting out for a three years' cruise to the Pacific Ocean, and reported, 19th. July, to
               Captain Downes for duty.[list of the officers of the Macedonian, not transcribing now <pb n="20"/>...] Officers and crew in number
               422.</p>
            <p>The equipment of the Macedonian was completed September the 19th. and on Sunday the 20th. 1818, we sailed from Boston with a fine
               breeze from W. S. W.</p>
            <p>On the 27th. of September, Latitude 36<!-- degrees --> N. Longtitude 56<!-- degrees --> W. we were dismasted in a hurricane--during the
               night it blew immoderately, causing a heavy mountainous sea--at 5 o'clock in the morning the mizen mast fell, carrying with it three
               fine boats; besides which, by 7 o'clock, we lost, by force of the wind, every sail, and every spar, except the bowsprit and fore and
               main masts, which were badly sprung. During the gale life lines were rove fore and aft to enable the officers and crew to keep their
               footing upon the decks--no human voice could be heard above the storm, so fiercely did the wind rage that to communicate an order it
               was necessary to give it in a subdued, instead of a loud, voice close to the ear of the seaman. The hull remained tight and sound, but
               the ship was otherwise a complete wreck. We lost overboard the captain of the mizen top--the life buoy was cut adrift, but no human aid
               could avail him: the poor fellow was abandoned to his fate</p>
            <pb n="21"/>
            <p>At meridian of the 28th. the gale abated to which may be ascribed our escape from foundering; for our situation was at one time
               exceedingly dangerous. All hands were now employed rigging jury-masts, and preparing the ship to return to port. Norfolk, Virginia,
               being the most convenient place, at which to refit, we directed our course thither, where we arrived, and anchored off the Navy Yard,
               October the 10th.</p>
            <p>Our refit being complete, on the 6th. of November we sailed from Norfolk, and received three hearty cheers from the inhabitants as we
               passed the Town. On the 5th. December we saw the Island St Jago, one of the cape de Verds, saw also the Island Fuego, of the same
               group. We crossed teh Equator December the 12th, at teh 25th. degree of west longitude, adn met with light airs and calms, and rain and
               frequent light<del>e</del>ning. Dad Neptune, with his wife Amphitrite, and their retinue, came on board, and went through the usual
               ceremonies of crossing the Line--a visit much better omitted than observed, on board a man of war.</p>
            <p>You will see, my sons, by what follows, that the crew of the Macedonian were not without their amuseuments.</p>
            <p>Written hand bills were distributed about the ship, giving notice that, on the evening of Christmas, a play, called the Weathercock,
               with an after piece entitled the Sailor's Fortune, would be performed: the author-<pb n="22"/>ship of the latter piece was claimed by
               D.C.B. carpenter's yeoman of the frigate. By permission of Captain Downs, the play and farce were acted, affording a novel treat to the
               officers and crew of the ship.</p>
            <p>On new year evening, the play of the Weathercock was again performed, after which we were entertained with the Cobbler and his
               Daughter, interspersed with songs &amp;, the whole got up, and the farce written, by our indefatigable <hi>author</hi> and
                  <hi>actor</hi> D.C.B. carpenter's yeoman. A criticism of the whole performance appeared in the Thespian Critic and Theatrical
               Review, a paper written and edited on board by some of the crew--of which the following is a copy.</p>
         </div>
         <div>
            <head>THE THESPIAN CRITIC AND THEATRICAL REVIEW.</head>
            <fw>No. 2--vol. I. JANUARY 2nd. 1819. 12 1/2 cents single.</fw>
            <head type="sub">THEATRICAL</head>
            <p>The Thespian Theatre was opened last evening for the second time, with the following entertainment of the Weathercock--and the Cobbler
               and his Daughter; Tristram by Mr. D.C.B. from the Theatre Royal. As expectation is always on tipto<add>e</add> at the <hi>debut</hi> of
               a new performer, and his merits and demerits occasion much animadversion, we have taken the trouble of minutely observing this new
               performer's beginning to give our <pb n="23"/>friends an impartial account of him; and we must say that our expectations were much
               disappointed, particularly with regard to his tautology and his gesticulation.</p>
            <p>In act 1st scene 1st, for saying "did you never hear of Demosthenes the Athenean orator &amp;," he repeats, did you never hear of
               De--mo--thens the A--the--an orator--certainly the most vulgar pronunciation. In his next speech of "I think I see him now awaking
               &amp;," his gesticulations were so violent that it reminded us of a frantic bedlamite, and seemed possessed with the idea that the more
               noise there was, the more admirable his performance. Again he says "one soul a--ni--ha--mates &amp;, for animates, Where he picked this
               jargon, or whether in his deep researches after literature, he conceives he has found a more correct manner of pronounciation than his
               contemporaries Johnson or Walker, we must leave the public to judge. Again, while conversing with Sneer, (Mr. Williams of the fore
               top,) to personate Juliet in saying "Oh that I were a glove upon that hand &amp;," his grimace is so intolerable, that it was painful
               to observe him; and he either forgot or was ignorant that, in addressing Juliet, he ought to have bended one knee; but no, with his
               finger pointed as if to command silence of his Juliet that she may hear his rhapsody: But of all the canting, noisey Billingsgate
               slang, his speech of a Soldier, a General &amp;, is made to represent to a hair: his eyes<pb n="24"/>roll, his chest is extended, his
               limbs compressed into the form of the letter S, and he makes the whole house tremble while he wars it out, and at intervals, bellowing
               like a child crying for a piece of bread and butter; but when he takes his sword--then comes the tug of war, and he fancies that
               admiration sits on every countenance, and he dances from one end of the stage to the other like a dancing bear. Again--in the scene
               between Tristram and the gardener--for "vile habilaments," he repeats--vile ha--bit--a--ments--what he means, no one could form an
               idea, unless it was by the action of throwing off his clothes; but enough for the present. We could point out a number of other
               material instances of defect; but hope that these will infuse into him a wish to correct his manners and pronounciation.</p>
            <p>Old Fickle by Franey, steerage servant<note>A steerage servant is a servant in the steerage, preparing meals and generally caring for
                  midshipment, or young officers in training. This is unique position in a ship because the steerage servant is likely well-known to
                  these young officers, but is not equal to them. This person is also not working alongside the able-bodied seamen (though he may be
                  bunking with them in separate quarters). The most important thing to note is that this performer gets kind criticism--it would seem
                  the reviewer knows him. This suggests that the reviewer was a midshipman</note>, a veteran--on the whole were much entertained by
               him and the performance of the character, though we hope he will be rather less forgetful on another night; and we sincerely believe
               that he will be a valuable acquisition to our Theatre.</p>
            <p>Miss Variella, by Williams of the carpenter's crew, --"grace in all <hi>her</hi>steps, heaven in <hi>her</hi> eye, in every gesture
               dignity and love."</p>
            <p>Briefwit, Mr. H, as stiff a piece mechanism and greater than the author intended him I dare say, for he was both briefwit and
               briefless. Sneer Mr. W with a<pb n="25"/>little improvement will do well in those characters. The piece went off without either many
               marks of approbation or disapprobation, and we hope that the piece will not be resumed without some attention being paid to the errors
               and defects pointed out.</p>
            <p>The Pantomime was so wretchedly performed that even the name of it would have been incomprehensible, unless we had seen it in the play
               bills.</p>
            <p>The songs were however, very well, but the subject too pointed; though we believe unintentionally so by the author. We were glad to see
               a full house on the commencement, as, without that, the expense could not be continued. We saw the side boxes were filled with Naval
               Heroes--some of distinction and rank. We have been thus particular with the faults of Mr. D.C.B., not with the wish to dishearten him;
               but to lead him to improvement, that he may thereby reap the reward of his exertion and talents.</p>
         </div>
         <div>
            <p>About this time an opposition paper appeared called the "Macedonian Scourge," --the following remarks are taken from paper No. 7.</p>
         </div>
         <div>
            <head><hi>Editorial</hi></head>
            <p>The Editor of this paper is really sorry that the remarks contained in his paper of January the third should have been of such a nature
               as to draw forth the "ire" of the gentleman who heads the Thespian Band. That a gentleman of his qualifications should have recourse to
               caricature for the purpose of defaming <pb n="26"/>him, (who would be the last to injure the Thespian Throng,) is really astonishing.
               With pleasure do we appeal to an enlightened public for an opinion of the following, which was made with no other view than to maintain
               the dignity of the stage, and that lustre which spreads it refulgent beams around the personage of this modern Othello,</p>
            <p>Theatrical Entertainment, January 2nd. 1819. Last evening the crew of the Macedonian frigate were politely favoured with a rich repast
               of Theatrical labour in the display of the Weathercock, and a pantomime of the Cobbler and his Daughter. We hope our subscribers will
               excuse us for a digression from our accustomed mode of issuing this paper in noticing the <hi>Dramatis Personae</hi> of those
               celebrated pieces. Tristram, that most important part of the Weathercock, was assigned to the <hi>natural</hi> and <hi>acquired</hi>
               abilities of Mr. David C. Bunnel, who has for a length of time appeared with so much honor to himself, and advantage to the community,
               upon the Theatres of the Congress and Macedonian frigates. He is not, however, without his imperfections, and in reminding him of them,
               we have not only the stage at heart; but that of his own welfare on the stage, and that to which he may be translated.</p>
            <p>In the part which relates to his having arrived to the acme of perfection in the study of the Law, and the learned speech which he
               makes to prove that he possesses that<pb n="27"/> fund of knowledge, we discover that his pronounciation is totally incorrect, as he
               differs from Johnson, Walker, and others. In pronouncing Demosthenes, he says "De--mo--thens, which must be disgusting to those who are
               familiar with pointing and diction. In another part he says the Ane--than instead of the Athenean Orator. We hope that he will make it
               his study to repair the damages done to the King's English by a proper adherence to the rules of pronounciation, in order that the
               brilliancy of his Theatrical abilities may not be tinged by imperfection which require little or no gumption to remove. </p>
            <p>in regard to "Williams" of the fore top, we doubt not but that he possesses more assurance than generally falls to the lot of mankind.
               It is not within the compass of our power to conceive what it was that actuated Williams to embark in that line of life, for which he
               has neither earthly or heavenly capacity; and we are at a loss to know what will cause him to recede from that line of life which ruins
               his judgement, and consigns his reputation to merited contempt and just indignation.</p>
            <p>In regard to old Fickle, great allowances should be made. A little of that <hi>twang</hi> which seems to be forced more than natural,
               should give way for more ease and elegance in pronounciation, together with a more retentive memory, that recourse need not be had to
               written papers in presence of the audience.</p>
            <p>Great credit is due to the unwearied exertions of<pb n="28"/> "Fanigan," who has been zealously employed in getting up the scenery
               &amp; &amp;. One gross mistake however, caught our eye as soon as we entered the room, which was a Turkey Buzzard substituted for the
               American coat of arms: without this, the scenery was in every respect complete.</p>
            <p>"Goodfellow," whom it seems is a new hand at the bellows, did not more than rise to mediocrity: But his articulation at the time
               Tristram discovers him in the capacity of a gardener, gave evident proof of his being likely to prove a great acquisition to the
               Thespian Band.</p>
            <p>Briefwit, alias Horton of the fore top, was both dull and tedious. Tameness was perceivable in every gesture, which may be attributed
               to his being totally unaquainted with the Latin tongue, which which his part abounded. Let the Manager hereafter be cautious how he
               disposes of those parts of the play on which depend solely the merit or demerit of the performers.</p>
            <p>Variella was immeasurably disgusting. Her appearance denoted a girl who had been rioting in all the pleasures which fancy could bestow
               from her earliest infancy, with a countenance which denied all shame, and which had not felt a blush since she entered her teens; she
               labored through her part without the least display of any thing like gesture or simplicity of manner which would even have caused the
               spectators of an inverted comedy to smile.</p>
            <pb n="29"/>
            <p>In taking a retrospect of the whole, we cannot say that it crowns every thing that was ever presented to our view, If these gentle
               admonitions should be of any avail, we will be foremost in noticing it after the next performance; but if the reverse, we shall
               continue to hold them up as subjects of severe criticism, and exclaim that we have not nor shall we ne'er look upon their like
               again."</p>
         </div>


      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
