<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title level="m" type="main">Extracts from "Outbreak in Jeddah in June 1858. Papers</title>
            <author>Various diplomats</author>
            <editor>Mary Isbell</editor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcription, encoding, and notes</resp>
               <name xml:id="initials">Mary Isbell</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>2018</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>TAPAS</publisher>
            <date>2018</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International License. </p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <monogr>
                  <editor>not yet known</editor>
                  <title>Outbreak at Jeddah in June 1858. Papers.</title>
                  <idno type="callno">National Archives--accessed through trial of database</idno>
                  <imprint>
                     <date>1867</date>
                     <note type="project">extracts of foreign office correspondence</note>
                  </imprint>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <particDesc>
            <listPerson>

               <person>
                  <persName xml:id="Edgell">Harry Edmund Edgell</persName>
                  <note>Harry Edmund Edgell joined the Chesapeake as Commodore after the period chronicled in the issues included in this edition. He
                     was an enthusiastic supporter of The Young Idea. In <hi rend="italics">Martello Tower" in China, and the Pacific in H.M.S.
                        "Tribune," 1856-60</hi>, Francis Martin Norman recounts Edgell's enthusiastic support for a shipboard theatrical aboard H.M.S.
                     Tribune in 1857, when he was captain of the ship. Edgell composed the prologue for the play and painted the drop-scene (50). The
                     National Maritime Museum at Greenwich (NMM) holds over 300 watercolors by Edgell, including some undertaken during the cruise
                     chronicled in The Young Idea. The NMM's biographical note on Edgell reads as follows: "Edgell was promoted to lieutenant in 1828,
                     to commander in 1837 and to captain in 1846. He was appointed to command the Tribune in 1855 when she was in the Crimea. During
                     this commission she went to the Pacific and finally to China. In 1857 Edgell was the Senior Naval Officer at Hong Kong and he
                     transferred into the Bittern tender commanding the gun boats on the Canton River during the hostilities with the Chinese. In 1858
                     be was given command of the squadron in Indian waters, during which time he commanded the Chesapeake and later the Retribution.
                     The latter returned to England and was paid off in 1860. Edgell had no further active employment and was promoted on the retired
                     list, reaching the rank of vice-admiral in 1871."</note>
               </person>
               <person>
                  <persName xml:id="Watson">Commodore Rundle Burges Watson</persName>
                  <note>Excerpts from “Watson, Rundle Burges” by <bibl><author>by J.K. Laughton, rev. Andrew Lambert</author></bibl> for the
                           <bibl><title>Oxford Dictionary of National Biography</title></bibl>: <quote>"Watson, Rundle Burges (1809–1860), naval
                        officer, was the eldest son of Captain Joshua Rowley Watson (1772–1810). He entered the navy in November 1821, and was
                        promoted lieutenant on 7 October 1829. [...] On 23 December 1842 he was advanced to post rank, and on 24 December was made a
                        CB. [...] In December 1852 [Watson] was appointed to the new steam frigate Impérieuse (50 guns), then, and for some years
                        later, considered one of the finest ships in the navy. In 1854 she was sent into the Baltic in advance of the fleet, Watson
                        being senior officer of the squadron of small vessels appointed to watch the breaking up of the ice, and to see that no
                        Russian warships got to sea. It was an arduous service well performed. The Impérieuse continued with the flying squadron in
                        the Baltic during the campaigns of 1854 and 1855, and until the signing of peace in March 1856. As the senior officer of the
                        frigate squadron, and generally on detached service, Watson demonstrated the highest standards of seamanship, judgement, and
                        leadership. After the peace the Impérieuse was sent to the North American station; she returned to England and was paid off
                        early in 1857. From May 1856 until his death Watson was naval aide-de-camp to the queen. In June 1859 he was appointed
                        captain-superintendent of Sheerness Dockyard, where he died on 5 July 1860. An officer of great ability, Watson was one of the
                        last great sailing-ship captains, and the first frigate captain of the steam era."</quote></note>
               </person>

               <person>
                  <persName xml:id="Namik_Pacha">Namik Pacha</persName>
                  <note>cite one of the articles on the uprising</note>
               </person>
            </listPerson>
            <listOrg>
               <org xml:id="Pelorus">
                  <note>HMS Pelorus was a Royal Navy screw corvette with twenty-one guns in the Pearl class. She was launched on February 5, 1858 and
                     her masting and fitting-out was completed on September 10, 1857. She was 200 feet long, 40 feet 4 inches at the broadest point,
                     with a depth in the hold of 23 feet 11 inches. As Lyon and Winfield explain, "Corvette designs were rapidly enlarged over the
                     1860s, as the corvette began to take over the traditional role of policing the high seas. To this end they were all built as
                     steam auxiliaries, designed to cruise under sail" (207). HMS Pelorus was broken up for parts at Devonport on February 3, 1869.
                     David Lyon and Rif Winfield, The Sail &amp; Steam Navy List: All the Ships of the Royal Navy, 1815–1889 (London: Chatham
                     Publishing), 2004.</note>
               </org>
               <org>
                  <orgName xml:id="Roebuck">Roebuck</orgName>
                  <note>HMS Roebuck was a Royal Navy despatch vessel with 5 guns in the Intrepid class. She was launched on March 22, 1856 and her
                     masting and fitting-out was completed on August 25, 1857. She was 200 feet long, 179 feet 5 1/4 inches at the broadest point,
                     with a depth in the hold of 14 feet 6 inches. She was built for a company of 100 men. As Lyon and Winfield explain, "The outbreak
                     of the Russian War demonstrated the need for numerous manoeuvrable, shallow-draught vessels for coastal and inshore operations in
                     the Baltic and Black Seas. Six small screw steamers of the Arrow Class were approved to be built by contract in the Thames [...]"
                     (218). The Roebuck was one of twenty additional vessels ordered in 1855 (218-219). David Lyon and Rif Winfield, The Sail &amp;
                     Steam Navy List: All the Ships of the Royal Navy, 1815–1889 (London: Chatham Publishing), 2004.</note>
               </org>
               <org>
                  <orgName xml:id="Cyclops">Cyclops</orgName>
                  <note>HMS Cyclops was a Royal Navy steam vessel with six guns in the Cyclops class. She was launched on July 10, 1839. She was 190
                     feet 3 inches long, 163 feet 6 inches at the broadest point, with a depth in the hold of 37 feet 6 inches. She was built for a
                     company of 175 to 200 men. As Lyon and Winfield explain, the ship was re-armed in 1856 "with 2x 68 pdrds (95cwt) on the pivots
                     and 4 x 10in (84cwt) on the broadside trucks." They also explain that she "was fitted 1856/57 to assist with the laying of the
                     Atlantic cable (151). David Lyon and Rif Winfield, The Sail &amp; Steam Navy List: All the Ships of the Royal Navy, 1815–1889
                     (London: Chatham Publishing), 2004. </note>
               </org>
               <org>
                  <orgName xml:id="Chesapeake">Chesapeake</orgName>
                  <note>HMS Chesapeake was a Royal Navy screw frigate with fifty-one guns in the Forte (or Imperieuse) class, which was one of several
                     classes including the thirty new wooden screw frigates completed between 1849 and 1865 (197). She was built in dry dock, launched
                     on September 7, 1855, and her masting and fitting-out was completed on August 28, 1857. She was 212 feet long, 50 feet 2 inches
                     at the broadest point, with a depth in the hold of 16 feet and 9 inches. She was built for a company of 515 men. The Chesapeake
                     was sold in 1867 to be broken up for parts at Charlton (200). David Lyon and Rif Winfield, The Sail &amp; Steam Navy List: All
                     the Ships of the Royal Navy, 1815–1889 (London: Chatham Publishing), 2004.</note>
               </org>
            </listOrg>
         </particDesc>
      </profileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>column breaks have not been retained, superscript has not been retained. Individual paragraphs have not been captured, making it seem
               like an entire contribution is one complete paragraph, which is not the case. Only the beginning of most contributions have been
               transcribed, followed by [...] indicating additional content to be transcribed. Where there is no title, "No Title" is used as the
               header.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <pb n="5"/>

         <div n="11">
            <head>Precis of Captain Pullen's Letter to the Secretary to the Admiralty, dated Jeddah, June 25, 1858.</head>
            <p>ON the evening of the 15th of June the rising of the Mahometans took place. It originated among the Hadramouts, or mercantile community
               of Jeddah.</p>
            <p>The attacks on the English and French Consulates, and the Christian inhabitants, were simultaneous. The Christians were principally
               Greeks. Mr. Page, after being cut to pieces, was thrown out of a window. M. Eveillard, the French Consul, was shot, and his wife cut
               down with a yataghan. The number massacred amounts to twenty-one, and perhaps more.</p>
            <p>Heard of the rising at 9:30 P.M., when two naked Greeks came on board in a small canoe. Later at night two more came off.</p>
            <p>The officers of the vessel had been in the bazars up to 6 P.M., without observing anything unusual. Though the Government would be able
               to afford sufficient protection.</p>
            <p>[...skipping ahead to get to the flag bit]</p>
            <p>Awaited the arrival of the Governor-General from Mecca, expected on the 19th.</p>
            <p>Learnt, on the 20th, that he had arrived.</p>
            <p>Demanded, in the name of the Christian world, that justice should be done.</p>
            <p>On the 22nd the Pasha called on me, and requested that the ship "Eranee" should be delivered up to him, and at his urgent written
               solicitation gave her up.</p>
            <p>Held him responsible for the ship till the decision of Her Majesty's Government.</p>
            <p>Have given a passage to Suez to a Turkish courier wiht despatches for Constantinople.</p>
            <p>The papers of the ship "Eranee," and the documents connected with her seizure, were destroyed at the English Consulate on the 15th. The
               Pasha states that the seizure of the "Eranee" was the cause of the massacre. The papers of twenty other British ships were also
               destroyed at the Consulate. Both the owners of the "ERanee" are British subjects.</p>
            <p>The Pasha states that Saleli Ben Johur, one of the owners of the "Eranee, is an Ottoman subject, although his vessel sailed under
               British colours. Up to the 15th he was considered British. The Pasha wrongly states that she "Eranee" only reassumed Turkish colours.
               By her register it appears she was built at Portsmouth, New Hampshire (America), and seems to have been since owned by persons entitled
               by law to be owners of British ships.</p>
            <p>The proceedings on teh "Eranee," by the Kaimakam's Commercial Court, were protested against by Furudj Yusu (acting for Mr. Page during
               his short absence), on the please of its incompetency to judge between two British subjects. Saleli Ben Johur said he would become an
               Ottoman subject, and teh Kaimakam allowed him to hoist the Turkish flag, but, on Furudj Yusu's renewed protest, ordered him to haul it
               down. He again, after twelve days, hoisted [still need to get these images]</p>
         </div>
         <pb n="9"/>
         <div n="15">
            <head>The Earl of Malmesbury to Sir H. Bulwer.</head>
            <p>(Telegraphic.) Foreign Office, July 15, 1858, 3 P.M.<!-- This isn't encoded correctly yet --></p>
            <p>The accounts from Jeddah and Suez, by Captain Pullen, of the "Cyclops," show the worst anti-Christian spirit as existing in those
               places and complete inefficiency in the authorities. We cannot be trifled with on this case of Jeddah, and even great political
               objects, as they regard our alliance with the Porte, must yield to the paramount principle of supporting Christan and British prestige
               in those regions</p>
            <p>It is not enough to send a General to Jeddah. Troops are wanted there, but, above all, a public execution of the murderers immediately.
               The Pasha must have the power of life and death given him at once, without tedious references to Constantinople. WE have ordered three
               ships, with Marines, to Jeddah, and shall seize the place if justice is not speedily obtained. You will state this to the Grand Vizier,
               and without reserve, and insist without intermission.</p>
         </div>
         <pb n="25"/>
         <div n="51">
            <head>Sir H. Bulwer to the Earl of Malmesbury.--(Received July 26, 7:20 A.M.)</head>
            <p>(Telegraphic.) Therapia, July 24, 1858, 10 P.M. <!-- This isn't encoded correctly yet --></p><p>The Turkish flag is to be at once taken
            down from the vessel seized by Namick Pasha, and its ultimate fate decided by an inquiry.</p><p>ON the other points the French Ambassador
               and myself have both required what your Lordship says teh British Government demanded.</p><p>The Sultan gives out of his own purse a
                  present to the sufferers, and pensions to the families of the Consuls; but this is not to interfere with the imposition of a
                  contribution on the inhabitants of Jeddah</p><p>The messenger just arrived. In regard to Jeddah, let me clearly explain: there is no
                  hesitation here about executing; the murderers in any number; but the law forbids a Pasha to inflict death without the Sultan's
                  order. This order is dispatched, and will get to Jeddah as soon as possible. What the Grand Vizier asks is, to allow of its arrival
                  before requiring the punishment in question: because, if it is inflicted by the authority of the Sultan, the Mahometans will
                  probably submit; wheras, if inflicted by teh Christian Powers alone, a gneneral rising amongst the Mahometans in that part of the
                  world and elsewhere may follow: and for the sake of India it seems to myself very important we should be able to show clearly that
                  the Sultan, as the head of the faith, is on our side. Just think of this, and no doubt of the intentions of people here. They will
                  do anything, but I will continue to hurry them, and keep up their alarm.</p>
         </div><pb n="42"/><div n="78"><head>Sir H. Bulwer to the Earl of Malmesbury.--(Received August 6)<!-- not yet encoded correctly
         --></head><p>No. 86<lb/>My Lord, Constantinople, July 27, 1858. My Lord</p><p>, I INCLOSE to you a report furnished me by M. Thouvenel of the
            proceedings at Jeddah. It was written by an eye-witness, the Chancelier of the French Consulate, who, together with the French Consul's
            daughter, escaped the general massacre.</p><p>According to this account the behaviour of Namick Pasha in relation to the "Eranee," was by
               no means free from blame.</p><p>The papers which I transmit, and which are found in the Chancery here, fully prove that the proprietor
                  was an Englishman, or at least claimed and enjoyed British protection. The conduct of the Pasha, however, in suppressing the riot
                  and siezing the ringleaders, seems, directly he entered the town, to have been prompt and energetic; and although his not executing
                  those who had been guilty of these atrocious crimes is to be regretted, it must not be forgotten that he acted in this manner
                  according to law, and, moreover, according to a law which the Sultan has enacted at teh recommendation of Christian
                  Powers.</p><p>[skipping some here]</p><p>[...]it is not to be forgotten that the Arab population are not willingly subjected to
                     Turkish contronl, and are frequently in rebellion against the authority of the Ottoman Government.</p><p>The Sovereign of this
                        Empire possesses, as I have said in my telegraphic message of the 26th, notwithstanding these partial outbreaks, a great
                        general authority and moral power, derived from the prestige which belongs to him as guardian of the Holy Cities; and I cannot
                     help thinking that it might be of importance to us (with respect to the Mahometan population generally, and even in respect to
                     the Mahometan population in India) to be able to produce a manifest sign of his displeasure at the blood-thirsty and fanatical
                     spirit which has recently inflicted such disgrace on the Moslem name.</p><p>I am, for this reason, very anxious that the late
                        massacre at Jeddah should be punished by the Sultan's officers and at the Sultan's orders; and if your Lordship shares my
                        opinion, it may be advisable to make such arrangements as would render it certain that Ismail Pasha and the reinforcements he
                        is to carry with him, and more especially that hte firman which confers the power of inflicting immediate execution on the
                        criminals, shoudl arrive at Jeddah before our forces appear there.</p><p>These forces, once on the spot, it would be difficult
                        for them not to act; and if they did act in the name of a Christian Power, I will not say taht it is certain, but it not
                        immprobable, that such an event might be followed by an immediate rising of the Mohometans in that part of the world, and
                        general outbreaks and massacres in various parts of this Empire, to say nothing of the effect it might have in teh Mahometan
                        portion of our dominions [signed, Henry L. Bulwer--need to encode this correctly]</p></div><pb n="56"/><div
                           n="88"><head>Inclosure 4 in No. 88<lb/>Captain Pullen to Namick Pasha</head><p>M. le Gouverneur-General "Cyclops," Jeddah, June 21, 1858</p><p>ON
                              your announcing to me your arrival at this place yesterday morning, you requested, previous to delivering to me the
                              Christians who had escaped the bloody massacre of the 15th instant, an interview.</p><p>Your Excellency is aware how readily I went on shore, the first object of my solicitude being the safety of all who sought protection of the
               British flag.</p><p>At my demand, it was arranged with your Excellency that the French and English colours should be
                                    hoisted the following morning of the main of this ship, side by side; that the boats being fully manned and armed,
                                 should proceed to the landing-place; that the English and French colours, being then advanced to the front, should
                                 receive a salute of twenty-one guns from the fort; that an armed procession should then form, and, with colours
                                 flying, proceed through the town, passing the residencies of the English and French Consuls, and, finally, thence a
                                 funeral party would proceed to the burial-ground, where the murdered Consuls lie, the service for teh dead read by
                                 the Chaplain of this ship, and military honours paid to the remains.
                     </p><p>Your Excellency was good enough to accompany the procession as far as the French Consulate.</p><p>I have now another duty
                        to discharge, and what I then verbally demanded, I now require at your hands.</p><p>Excellency, the blood of the murdered
                           calls for retribution, for a justice so stern, so terrible in its example, that throughout the land men will hear of the
                           massacre which took place, and, at the same time, of the punishment which followed</p><p>Excellency, I ask for this
                              justice, not in the name of England or France alone, but in the name of the whole Christian world. Protestants,
                              Catholics, Greeks, and Copts, have alike been barbarously murdered, and for all I demand justice. [...more, but stopping
                           here]</p></div><pb n="57"/><div n="89"><head>Acting Consul-General Green to the Earl of Malmesbury.--(Received August
                              18.)</head><p>(Telegraphic.) Alexandria, August 13, 1858. <!-- not yet transcribed correctly --></p><p>HER Majesty's
                                 ship "Cyclops" arrived at Suez from Jeddah last night. I have received the following telegram from Captain
                                 Pullen:--</p><p>'Cyclops arrived at Jeddah 23rd July. Namick Pasha at Mecca. Satisfaction demanded, and letter sent
                                    to Kaimakam under flying seal, saying, if no satisfactory answer received in thirty-six hours, shall proceed to
                                    extremities.</p><p>On the morning of the 25th, forty hours having intervened from time of sending despatch, and no
                                    reply, commended bombarding on the town at intervals.</p><p>Fourteen or fifteen buggalows burnt and
                                       destroyed.</p><p>At 11 A.M., letter from Pasha, not satisfactory; resumed operations, and continued
                                          occasionally until evening of 26th, both from boats and ships, with shot, shell, and rockets</p><p>27th.
                                             Troops arrived, 507 Bashi-Bazouks. Time given to land.</p><p>28th. Pasha arrived; comes on board next
                                                day: can come to satisfactory arrangements; cannot execute murderers, but has them confined. States
                                                that has not the power of life and death; time extended to allow pilgrims to embark.</p><p>30th. 'Lady
                                                Canning' leaves for Yembo wiht Moorish Princes. Depositions of murderers sent; proved guilt by their
                                                own local Courts. Their execution insisted upon on the morning of the 2nd instant; and not complied
                                                with by the evening of the 4th.</p><p>Commenced bombarding again on morning of the 5th. Before a reply
                                                is received the 'Gabari' steamer arrived with troops; 480 Egyptians. Ismail Pasha commands, with power
                                                to satisfy just demands of England and France.</p><p>On the morning of the 6th, eleven murdersr
                                                   executed in sight of the town and shipping in port, and four more culprits to be sent to
                                                   Constantinople.</p><p>The 'Cyclops' left Jeddah on morning of the 7th instant, and has brought up a
                                                   messenger from the Pasha with despatches for Constantinople.</p><p>Mr. Vice-Consul Calvert has my despatches for the Admiralty, and leaves immediately.</p></div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
