<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title level="m" type="main">The Young Idea in Jeddah</title>
            <author>A.D. McArthur</author>
            <editor>Mary Isbell</editor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcription, encoding, and notes</resp>
               <name xml:id="initials">Mary Isbell</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>2018</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>TAPAS</publisher>
            <date>2018</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International License. </p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <monogr>
                  <editor>A.D. McArthur</editor>
                  <title>The Young Idea: A Naval Journal Edited on Board the H.M.S. Chesapeake in 1857, 1858 &amp; 1859 </title>
                  <idno type="callno">Edition created from copy in editor's private collection, only other known copy held at British Library:
                     1757.a.20/</idno>
                  <imprint>
                     <date>1867</date>
                     <biblScope>
                        <!-- type="pubPlace" -->
                        <ref type="address">170 Fleet Street, London, England</ref>
                        <name type="publisher">Paul Jerrard &amp; Son</name>
                     </biblScope>
                     <note type="project">Diamond Harbour Performance</note>
                  </imprint>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <particDesc>
            <listPerson>
               <person xml:id="A_D_McArthur">
                  <note>Alexander D. McArthur, a clerk, joined the Chesapeake on December 9th 1857. He was born on December 25th 1835 in Woolwich,
                     Kent, making him 21 when he came aboard. Census records for the town of Woolwich in 1851 reveal the family of John McAurthur, a
                     captain in the Royal Marines, who lived with his wife Mary E., a son James (a gentleman, aged 29), a son John (no occupation,
                     aged 27), a son Henry (a clerk in the wine trade, aged 17), a son Alexander D (a scholar, aged 15), a son Hanibal (no occupation,
                     aged 13), and a servant Esther Johnson (aged 20).</note>
                  <!--<bibl><<msIdentifier><msName>Muster Book of Her Majesty's Ship Chesapeake Commencing 1st January 1858 Ending 31st March 1858</msName>
                        <institution>National Archives at Kew</institution>
                     <idno>ADM 38/2884</idno>
                     </msIdentifier></bibl>
                  <bibl>
                  <bibl><msIdentifier><msName>Census Returns of England and Wales, 1851. Kew, Surrey, England</msName><institution>The National Archives of the
                     UK (TNA): Public Record Office (PRO)</institution>                       
                     </msIdentifier></bibl>-->
               </person>
               <person xml:id="J_W_L_Bampfield">
                  <note>Reverend John William Lewis Bampfield joined the Chesapeake on July 24th 1857 and was a regular contributor to and supporter
                     of The Young Idea. While his age is not recorded in the muster book, census records reveal that Bampfield was born in June of
                     1823, so he was in his mid-thirties during the cruise. He was commissioned as chaplain aboard a different royal naval vessel in
                     Port Royal, Jamaica before his arrival aboard the Chesapeake. His detailed journal provides an additional witness to The Young
                     Idea, providing fascinating points of contrast from the facsimile edition that McArthur had printed in 1867 and offering hints
                     about the authorship of contributions through his inclusion of the initials of authors (a marked list). </note>
               </person>
               <person xml:id="Edgell">
                  <note>Harry Edmund Edgell joined the Chesapeake as Commodore after the period chronicled in the issues included in this edition. He
                     was an enthusiastic supporter of The Young Idea. In <hi rend="italics">Martello Tower" in China, and the Pacific in H.M.S.
                        "Tribune," 1856-60</hi>, Francis Martin Norman recounts Edgell's enthusiastic support for a shipboard theatrical aboard H.M.S.
                     Tribune in 1857, when he was captain of the ship. Edgell composed the prologue for the play and painted the drop-scene (50). The
                     National Maritime Museum at Greenwich (NMM) holds over 300 watercolors by Edgell, including some undertaken during the cruise
                     chronicled in The Young Idea. The NMM's biographical note on Edgell reads as follows: "Edgell was promoted to lieutenant in 1828,
                     to commander in 1837 and to captain in 1846. He was appointed to command the Tribune in 1855 when she was in the Crimea. During
                     this commission she went to the Pacific and finally to China. In 1857 Edgell was the Senior Naval Officer at Hong Kong and he
                     transferred into the Bittern tender commanding the gun boats on the Canton River during the hostilities with the Chinese. In 1858
                     be was given command of the squadron in Indian waters, during which time he commanded the Chesapeake and later the Retribution.
                     The latter returned to England and was paid off in 1860. Edgell had no further active employment and was promoted on the retired
                     list, reaching the rank of vice-admiral in 1871."</note>
               </person>
               <person xml:id="George_Horner">
                  <note>George Horner, a bandsman, joined the Chesapeake on August 12, 1857. He was born in London in 1817. The muster book for the
                     Chesapeake claims to offer the first entry for George Horner, perhaps meaning this was his first time at sea.<bibl>Muster Book of
                        Her Majesty's Ship Chesapeake Commencing 1st January 1858 Ending 31st March 1858, held by the National Archives at Kew (ADM
                        38/2884)</bibl></note>
               </person>
               <person xml:id="James_Hammond">
                  <note>James Hammond, an ordinary seaman, joined the Chesapeake on August 12, 1857. He was born in London on November 12, 1837 and
                     served aboard HMS Eurydice just before joining the Chesapeake.<bibl>Muster Book of Her Majesty's Ship Chesapeake Commencing 1st
                        January 1859 Ending 31st March 1859, held by the National Archives at Kew (ADM
                     38/2886)</bibl><!-- note that this same information is available in the first muster book kept for the voyage; I looked later
                           because Hammond didn't appear on stage until later. --></note>
               </person>
               <person xml:id="Charles_Stewart">
                  <note>Charles Stewart, an ordinary seaman, joined the Chesapeake on May 23, 1857. He was born in London and served aboard HMS
                     Gladiator just before joining the Chesapeake. He was born in 1834.<bibl>Muster Book of Her Majesty's Ship Chesapeake Commencing
                        1st January 1858 Ending 31st March 1858, held by the National Archives at Kew (ADM 38/2884)</bibl></note>
               </person>
               <person xml:id="Thomas_Walsh">
                  <note>Thomas Walsh, an ordinary seaman, joined the Chesapeake on August 15, 1857. He was born in London in 1834 and served aboard
                     HMS Cressy just before joining the Chesapeake.<bibl>Muster Book of Her Majesty's Ship Chesapeake Commencing 1st January 1858
                        Ending 31st March 1858, held by the National Archives at Kew (ADM 38/2884)</bibl></note>
               </person>
               <person xml:id="Robert_Wilkinson">
                  <note>Robert Wilkinson, a private in the Royal Marines, joined the Chesapeake on July 25th 1857. He was born in Sitchfield,
                        Staffordshire.<bibl>Muster Book of Her Majesty's Ship Chesapeake Commencing 1st January 1858 Ending 31st March 1858, held by
                        the National Archives at Kew (ADM 38/2884)</bibl></note>
               </person>
               <person xml:id="Henry_Underhill">
                  <note>ordinary seaman from Alesford, 36 when coming aboard the Chesapeake<bibl>Muster Book of Her Majesty's Ship Chesapeake
                        Commencing 1st January 1858 Ending 31st March 1858, held by the National Archives at Kew (ADM 38/2884)</bibl>
                  </note>
               </person>
               <person xml:id="John_Welsh">
                  <note>Though the first playbill lists this performer as "John Walshe," making it possible that this actor is the person represented
                     by the "John Welsh" in the muster log. John Welsh is an ordinary seaman who joined the Chesapeake on February 20, 1857. He was
                     born in Mayo<bibl>Muster Book of Her Majesty's Ship Chesapeake Commencing 1st January 1858 Ending 31st March 1858, held by the
                        National Archives at Kew (ADM 38/2884)</bibl></note>
               </person>
               <person xml:id="Henry_Montagu">
                  <note>Henry Montagu, yeoman of signals, joined the Chesapeake on July 28, 1857 after serving aboard HMS President. He was born in
                     St. Hilliers, Jersey (the Channel Islands) in 1826, making him 32 at the time of the performance.<bibl>Muster Book of Her
                        Majesty's Ship Chesapeake Commencing 1st January 1858 Ending 31st March 1858, held by the National Archives at Kew (ADM
                        38/2884)</bibl></note>
               </person>
               <person xml:id="Isaac_Wright">
                  <note>Isaac Wright, an ordinary sailor 2nd class, joined the Chesapeake on September 4th 1857. He was born in Sunderland in 1835,
                     making him 23 at the time of the performance.<bibl>Muster Book of Her Majesty's Ship Chesapeake Commencing 1st January 1858
                        Ending 31st March 1858, held by the National Archives at Kew (ADM 38/2884)</bibl></note>
               </person>
               <person xml:id="Henry_Hamilton">
                  <note>C. R. B. Hamilton (the only Hamilton in the musters) was a naval cadet who served aboard <orgName ref="Colossus">HMS
                        Colossus</orgName> before joining the Chesapeake on July 23, 1857. He was born in County Tyrone, Ireland in December of 1842,
                     making him 15 at the time the performance<bibl>Muster Book of Her Majesty's Ship Chesapeake Commencing 1st January 1858 Ending
                        31st March 1858, held by the National Archives at Kew (ADM 38/2884)</bibl></note>
               </person>
               <person xml:id="James_Brown">
                  <note>James Brown, an ordinary seaman, joined the Chesapeake on July 23, 1857, after serving aboard <orgName ref="Cuckoo">HMS
                        Cuckoo</orgName> until February 3, 1857. He was born at Sheerness on the 17th of January 1829, making him 28 at the time of
                     the performance<bibl>Muster Book of Her Majesty's Ship Chesapeake Commencing 1st January 1858 Ending 31st March 1858, held by the
                        National Archives at Kew (ADM 38/2884)</bibl></note>
               </person>
               <person xml:id="William_Connell">
                  <note>William T. Connell, an ordinary seaman, joined the Chesapeake on July 31 1857, after serving aboard HMS Eurydice until 17 June
                     1857. He was born in London in 1835, making him 27 at the time of the performance.<bibl>Muster Book of Her Majesty's Ship
                        Chesapeake Commencing 1st January 1858 Ending 31st March 1858, held by the National Archives at Kew (ADM
                     38/2884)</bibl></note>
               </person>
            </listPerson>
            <listOrg>
               <org xml:id="Pelorus">
                  <note>HMS Pelorus was a Royal Navy screw corvette with twenty-one guns in the Pearl class. She was launched on February 5, 1858 and
                     her masting and fitting-out was completed on September 10, 1857. She was 200 feet long, 40 feet 4 inches at the broadest point,
                     with a depth in the hold of 23 feet 11 inches. As Lyon and Winfield explain, "Corvette designs were rapidly enlarged over the
                     1860s, as the corvette began to take over the traditional role of policing the high seas. To this end they were all built as
                     steam auxiliaries, designed to cruise under sail" (207). HMS Pelorus was broken up for parts at Devonport on February 3, 1869.
                     David Lyon and Rif Winfield, The Sail &amp; Steam Navy List: All the Ships of the Royal Navy, 1815–1889 (London: Chatham
                     Publishing), 2004.</note>
               </org>
               <org xml:id="Roebuck">
                  <note>HMS Roebuck was a Royal Navy despatch vessel with 5 guns in the Intrepid class. She was launched on March 22, 1856 and her
                     masting and fitting-out was completed on August 25, 1857. She was 200 feet long, 179 feet 5 1/4 inches at the broadest point,
                     with a depth in the hold of 14 feet 6 inches. She was built for a company of 100 men. As Lyon and Winfield explain, "The outbreak
                     of the Russian War demonstrated the need for numerous manoeuvrable, shallow-draught vessels for coastal and inshore operations in
                     the Baltic and Black Seas. Six small screw steamers of the Arrow Class were approved to be built by contract in the Thames [...]"
                     (218). The Roebuck was one of twenty additional vessels ordered in 1855 (218-219). David Lyon and Rif Winfield, The Sail &amp;
                     Steam Navy List: All the Ships of the Royal Navy, 1815–1889 (London: Chatham Publishing), 2004.</note>
               </org>
               <org xml:id="Cyclops">
                  <note>HMS Cyclops was a Royal Navy steam vessel with six guns in the Cyclops class. She was launched on July 10, 1839. She was 190
                     feet 3 inches long, 163 feet 6 inches at the broadest point, with a depth in the hold of 37 feet 6 inches. She was built for a
                     company of 175 to 200 men. As Lyon and Winfield explain, the ship was re-armed in 1856 "with 2x 68 pdrds (95cwt) on the pivots
                     and 4 x 10in (84cwt) on the broadside trucks." They also explain that she "was fitted 1856/57 to assist with the laying of the
                     Atlantic cable (151). David Lyon and Rif Winfield, The Sail &amp; Steam Navy List: All the Ships of the Royal Navy, 1815–1889
                     (London: Chatham Publishing), 2004. </note>
               </org>
               <org xml:id="Chesapeake">
                  <note>HMS Chesapeake was a Royal Navy screw frigate with fifty-one guns in the Forte (or Imperieuse) class, which was one of several
                     classes including the thirty new wooden screw frigates completed between 1849 and 1865 (197). She was built in dry dock, launched
                     on September 7, 1855, and her masting and fitting-out was completed on August 28, 1857. She was 212 feet long, 50 feet 2 inches
                     at the broadest point, with a depth in the hold of 16 feet and 9 inches. She was built for a company of 515 men. The Chesapeake
                     was sold in 1867 to be broken up for parts at Charlton (200). David Lyon and Rif Winfield, The Sail &amp; Steam Navy List: All
                     the Ships of the Royal Navy, 1815–1889 (London: Chatham Publishing), 2004.</note>
               </org>
            </listOrg>
         </particDesc>
      </profileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>column breaks have not been retained, superscript has not been retained. Individual paragraphs have not been captured, making it seem
               like an entire contribution is one complete paragraph, which is not the case. Only the beginning of most contributions have been
               transcribed, followed by [...] indicating additional content to be transcribed. Where there is no title, "No Title" is used as the
               header.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <pb n="IMG_1453" facs="https://farm2.staticflickr.com/1754/40668619260_625db61c72_k_d.jpg"/>
         <div>
            <head>Theatricals.<note>(The article is very similar though a little less detailed in Bampfield in Bampfield. Bampfield attributes the
                  prologue (or perhaps the whole review) to "B." He also includes, after the prologue, "Many Officers &amp; men from the <orgName
                     ref="#Roebuck">Roebuck</orgName> honoured our performance with their presence. A supper was spread for the actors in the
                  fore-Cabin.</note></head>
            <p>On Wednesday Evening (June 9) our Theatrical Amateurs gave their first performance on board our ship. The pieces being the same as
               those which were performed in the Calcutta Theatre in February last, we may say little more than that they all did their parts well
               &amp; gave universal satisfaction to their audience. The disadvantages, however under which they laboured were very great. The
               construction of a ship being so unfavourable to sound, &amp; a strong breeze blowing at the time, their voices when at all lowered
               became almost inaudible to those at a distance. Hence much of the intent &amp; point of the pieces was entirely lost Even the old<pb
                  n="IMG_1453l" facs="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7829/32123610697_2ef4b4690a_k_d.jpg"/>miser's tragic acting became much of it
               dumb show. <persName ref="#Henry_Underhill">"Simon Siggels</persName> amusing hunger could hardly be appreciated and the "fair one" of
               the play <persName ref="#William_Connell">"Victorine"</persName> with her feminine tones, could scarcely be heard in any part of her
               speech The fault was not that of the actors, &amp; we would hope that judicious management, another time would render a second
               performance much more attractive. The robbers <persName ref="#John_Welsh">"Hans"</persName> &amp; <persName ref="#Isaac_Wright">"John
                  Brown"</persName> were as amusing as ever, &amp; perhaps were better heard than any. The light thrown on the stage was so
               indifferent that the play of the actor's features was completely lost</p>
            <p>"Bombastes" went off very well &amp; caused much laughter; but we are of opinion, that neither the polished drama, nor the refined
               burlesque will overtake so well with a ship's audience, as a good, broad, roaring comedy, in which comic action may supply the loss of
               words. We hope the managers will take our advice</p>
            <p>The "Irish Jig" by <persName ref="#Thomas_Walsh">T. Walsh</persName> was capital &amp; was loudly encored. A Gentleman who announced
               himself as "a rummy old Cadger" &amp; whom we fancy to have seen occasionally in our private circles, made his appearance on the stage
               between the acts, &amp; obtained great applause by his humorous singing; on being encored he gave an account of his sad fall from
               riches to poverty, but concluded with the poetic sentiment, a man's a man for a' "that"!!!<note>probably "Is There for Honest Poverty",
                  commonly known as "A Man's a Man for A' That" or "For a' That and a' That", 1795 song by Robert Burns</note></p>
            <p>On the whole we believe that our "Play" has given an amusing diversion to the ships company &amp; made a pleasant break in our stay at
               Diamond Harbour.</p>
            <lg>
               <head>PROLOGUE written expressly for the occasion</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>When Thespis first with modest skill began</l>
                  <l>To pain in glowing Verse the deeds of Man,</l>
                  <l>Green waving boughs were all the "scene" he tried</l>
                  <l>And Nature's sword a ready "stage" supplied.</l>
                  <l>so when our little Thespian band, essays</l>
                  <l>To win the guerdon of a shipmate's praise,</l>
                  <l>These pine plank decks shall be the stage we tread</l>
                  <l>These varied flags their simple scenery spread.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>A shipmate's praise is all the boon we claim</l>
                  <l>A shipmate's pleasure is our highest aim</l>
                  <l>'Tis ours to soothe the heart, to raise the smile,</l>
                  <l>And with gay thoughts your evening hours beguile;</l>
                  <l>'Tis ours to move at joyous mirth's behest,</l>
                  <l>call the light laugh, &amp; hail the merry jest;</l>
                  <l>'Tis ours to cheer the spririt dash'd with care,</l>
                  <l>To aid the drooping heart its woes to bear,</l>
                  <l>And while, beneath these sultry climes we roam,</l>
                  <l>To banish sorrow from our floating home.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Tonight again we bring before the scene</l>
                  <l>The noble <persName ref="#Charles_Stewart">"Adolphe"</persName> and fair <persName ref="#William_Connell"
                     >"Victorine"</persName></l>
                  <l>Once more the stern &amp; miserly <persName ref="#George_Horner">"Darnaud"</persName></l>
                  <l>Shall tell his tale of checquered care and woe.</l>
                  <l>Once more the merry <persName ref="#John_Welsh">"Hans"</persName> &amp; brave <persName ref="#Isaac_Wright">"John
                        Brown."</persName></l>
                  <l>Shall play their midnight pranks about the town</l>
                  <l>And <persName ref="#Henry_Underhill">"Simon Siggel"</persName> still record how nice</l>
                  <l>His soup &amp; beef &amp; "weal" boiled down with rice</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l><persName ref="#Henry_Montagu">King "Artaxominus"</persName> [y'clept?] the great</l>
                  <l>shall then be seen in all his regal state,</l>
                  <l><persName ref="#Charles_Stewart">"Fusbos"</persName> shall still with prudent art advise,</l>
                  <l>and <persName ref="#William_Connell">"Distaffina"</persName> charm the coldest eyes</l>
                  <l>While brave <persName ref="#Henry_Underhill">"Bombastes"</persName> burning deep with rage</l>
                  <l>shall wield his flashing sword, &amp; strut the stage</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Tonight, no unjust critic need we fear</l>
                  <l>No envious "Ditchers" find an entrance here</l>
                  <l>But honest faces smile upon our muse</l>
                  <l>And kindly hearts our largest faults excuse</l>
                  <l>so shall our Play to you more pleasing prove,</l>
                  <l>And while kind voices gen'rous praise award</l>
                  <l>Your heards approving, may your hands applaud.</l>
               </lg>
            </lg>
         </div>

      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
