<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title level="m" type="main">The Young Idea in Jeddah</title>
            <author>A.D. McArthur</author>
            <editor>Mary Isbell</editor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcription, encoding, and notes</resp>
               <name xml:id="initials">Mary Isbell</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>2018</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>TAPAS</publisher>
            <date>2018</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International License. </p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <monogr>
                  <editor>A.D. McArthur</editor>
                  <title>The Young Idea: A Naval Journal Edited on Board the H.M.S. Chesapeake in 1857, 1858 &amp; 1859 </title>
                  <idno type="callno">Edition created from copy in editor's private collection, only other known copy held at British Library:
                     1757.a.20/</idno>
                  <imprint>
                     <date>1867</date>
                     <biblScope>
                        <!-- type="pubPlace" -->
                        <ref type="address">170 Fleet Street, London, England</ref>
                        <name type="publisher">Paul Jerrard &amp; Son</name>
                     </biblScope>
                     <note type="project">outline of issues published off the coast of Jeddah</note>
                  </imprint>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>column breaks have not been retained, superscript has not been retained. Individual paragraphs have not been captured, making it seem
               like an entire contribution is one complete paragraph, which is not the case. Only the beginning of the contribution has been
               transcribed, followed by [...] indicating additional content to be transcribed.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <pb n="TYI1421"/>
         <div n="7" type="issue">
            <head type="main">"The Young Idea"</head>
            <head type="main">Chesapeake Chronicle and Weekly Journal</head>
            <head type="sub">Saturday 20th November 1858</head>
            <head type="sub">Vol 1. No 42</head>
            <div type="article">
               <p> Our stay at Jeddah has worn a very monotonous aspect. Strangers, to the shore, we have only been able to gaze from our bulwarks on
                  the far spreading sands, and barren hills of Arabia, and sigh to don the garment of some Mecca pilgrim, mount on the hump of some
                  fleet camel, and all Christian as we are, penetrate into the holiest shrines, and sanctuaries of Islam. [...]<pb n="TYI1422"/>[...]
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="article">
               <head>Sailing up the Red Sea.</head>
               <p>Sunday Morning 17 Octr. Having sailed with a fair breeze from Aden yesterday afternoon, we are this morning in sight of the straits
                  of Babel-Mandel. [...details the ship approaching Jeddah with the help of a Arab pilot named Abdullah...] <pb n="TYI1423"/>[...]</p>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <head>Tuesday 19 Octr 1858</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>The sun had past his highest point, the sea was calm &amp; bright</l>
                  <l>The ship was slowly urged along, by breezes soft and light</l>
                  <l>[...9 quatrains of verse describing a shark eating a midshipman's jacket and then being caught and eaten by the crew]</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="article">
               <head>The Late Comet.</head>
               <p>We are sorry that the very brief notes taken by "our own Observer", will not permit us to give any elaborate or scientific account
                  of this beautiful heavenly visitor. It was on teh Evening of Septr 30th after dropping anchor at Aden, that our attention was first
                  called to see teh bright stranger, which had made its appearance, unpredicted, &amp; unannounced among the celestial bodies of the
                  Northern Hemisphere.[...]<pb n="TYI1424"/>[...]</p>
            </div>
            <div type="Naval_Intelligence">
               <head>Naval Intelligence</head>
               <p>22nd Octr. H.M.S. Chesapeake arrived at Jeddah on Friday 22nd at 5 P.M. having been piloted in through the outer reefs by Mr Mayes
                  Master of the Cyclops. [...]</p>
            </div>
            <div type="Epitome">
               <head>Epitome</head>
               <p>On Monday Oct 25 preparations were made for the reception of His Excellency Nemuk Pacha, and the English &amp; French Commissioners,
                  but his Excellency being indiscposed after visiting the "Pelorus" was unable to visit us. The Commissioners however came on board
                  and inspected the ship.[...general reports of storms and boredom]</p>
            </div>
            <div type="Facetiae">
               <head>Facetiae</head>
               <p>A shocking punster, hearing that Jeddah was celebrated for Turquoise, said that if Turks &amp; Arabs were on unfriendly terms, no
                  doubt plenty of "Turk Wars" would be the result. [...other puns]</p>
            </div>
            <div type="Enigma">
               <head>Enigma</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>BOrne on the wing of yon dark plumag'd bird</l>
                  <l>High o'er the earth how oft I took my flight:[...three quatrains of a riddle]</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
