<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title level="m" type="main">The Young Idea in Jeddah</title>
            <author>A.D. McArthur</author>
            <editor>Mary Isbell</editor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcription, encoding, and notes</resp>
               <name xml:id="initials">Mary Isbell</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>2018</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>TAPAS</publisher>
            <date>2018</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International License. </p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <monogr>
                  <editor>A.D. McArthur</editor>
                  <title>The Young Idea: A Naval Journal Edited on Board the H.M.S. Chesapeake in 1857, 1858 &amp; 1859 </title>
                  <idno type="callno">Edition created from copy in editor's private collection, only other known copy held at British Library:
                     1757.a.20/</idno>
                  <imprint>
                     <date>1867</date>
                     <biblScope>
                        <!-- type="pubPlace" -->
                        <ref type="address">170 Fleet Street, London, England</ref>
                        <name type="publisher">Paul Jerrard &amp; Son</name>
                     </biblScope>
                     <note type="project">outline of issues published off the coast of Jeddah</note>
                  </imprint>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>


         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <particDesc>
            <listPerson>
               <person>
                  <persName xml:id="A_D_McArthur">Alexander D. McArthur</persName>
                  <note>Alexander D. McArthur, a clerk, joined the Chesapeake on December 9th 1857. He was born on December 25th 1835 in Woolwich,
                     Kent, making him 21 when he came aboard. Census records for the town of Woolwich in 1851 reveal the family of John McAurthur, a
                     captain in the Royal Marines, who lived with his wife Mary E., a son James (a gentleman, aged 29), a son John (no occupation,
                     aged 27), a son Henry (a clerk in the wine trade, aged 17), a son Alexander D (a scholar, aged 15), a son Hanibal (no occupation,
                     aged 13), and a servant Esther Johnson (aged 20).</note>
                  <bibl>Muster Book of Her Majesty's Ship Chesapeake Commencing 1st January 1858 Ending 31st March 1858, held by the National Archives
                     at Kew (ADM 38/2884)</bibl>
                  <bibl>Census Returns of England and Wales, 1851. Kew, Surrey, England: The National Archives of the UK (TNA): Public Record Office
                     (PRO), 1851.</bibl>
               </person>

               <person>
                  <persName xml:id="J_W_L_Bampfield">John William Lewis Bampfield</persName>
                  <note>Reverend John William Lewis Bampfield joined the Chesapeake on July 24th 1857 and was a regular contributor to and supporter
                     of The Young Idea. While his age is not recorded in the muster book, census records reveal that Bampfield was born in June of
                     1823, so he was in his mid-thirties during the cruise. He was commissioned as chaplain aboard a different royal naval vessel in
                     Port Royal, Jamaica before his arrival aboard the Chesapeake. His detailed journal provides an additional witness to The Young
                     Idea, providing fascinating points of contrast from the facsimile edition that McArthur had printed in 1867 and offering hints
                     about the authorship of contributions through his inclusion of the initials of authors (a marked list). </note>
               </person>
               <person>
                  <persName xml:id="Edgell">Harry Edmund Edgell</persName>
                  <note>Harry Edmund Edgell joined the Chesapeake as Commodore after the period chronicled in the issues included in this edition. He
                     was an enthusiastic supporter of The Young Idea. In <hi rend="italics">Martello Tower" in China, and the Pacific in H.M.S.
                        "Tribune," 1856-60</hi>, Francis Martin Norman recounts Edgell's enthusiastic support for a shipboard theatrical aboard H.M.S.
                     Tribune in 1857, when he was captain of the ship. Edgell composed the prologue for the play and painted the drop-scene (50). The
                     National Maritime Museum at Greenwich (NMM) holds over 300 watercolors by Edgell, including some undertaken during the cruise
                     chronicled in The Young Idea. The NMM's biographical note on Edgell reads as follows: "Edgell was promoted to lieutenant in 1828,
                     to commander in 1837 and to captain in 1846. He was appointed to command the Tribune in 1855 when she was in the Crimea. During
                     this commission she went to the Pacific and finally to China. In 1857 Edgell was the Senior Naval Officer at Hong Kong and he
                     transferred into the Bittern tender commanding the gun boats on the Canton River during the hostilities with the Chinese. In 1858
                     be was given command of the squadron in Indian waters, during which time he commanded the Chesapeake and later the Retribution.
                     The latter returned to England and was paid off in 1860. Edgell had no further active employment and was promoted on the retired
                     list, reaching the rank of vice-admiral in 1871."</note>
               </person>
               <person>
                  <persName xml:id="Watson">Commodore Rundle Burges Watson</persName>
                  <note>Excerpts from “Watson, Rundle Burges” by <bibl><author>by J.K. Laughton, rev. Andrew Lambert</author></bibl> for the
                           <bibl><title>Oxford Dictionary of National Biography</title></bibl>: <quote>"Watson, Rundle Burges (1809–1860), naval
                        officer, was the eldest son of Captain Joshua Rowley Watson (1772–1810). He entered the navy in November 1821, and was
                        promoted lieutenant on 7 October 1829. [...] On 23 December 1842 he was advanced to post rank, and on 24 December was made a
                        CB. [...] In December 1852 [Watson] was appointed to the new steam frigate Impérieuse (50 guns), then, and for some years
                        later, considered one of the finest ships in the navy. In 1854 she was sent into the Baltic in advance of the fleet, Watson
                        being senior officer of the squadron of small vessels appointed to watch the breaking up of the ice, and to see that no
                        Russian warships got to sea. It was an arduous service well performed. The Impérieuse continued with the flying squadron in
                        the Baltic during the campaigns of 1854 and 1855, and until the signing of peace in March 1856. As the senior officer of the
                        frigate squadron, and generally on detached service, Watson demonstrated the highest standards of seamanship, judgement, and
                        leadership. After the peace the Impérieuse was sent to the North American station; she returned to England and was paid off
                        early in 1857. From May 1856 until his death Watson was naval aide-de-camp to the queen. In June 1859 he was appointed
                        captain-superintendent of Sheerness Dockyard, where he died on 5 July 1860. An officer of great ability, Watson was one of the
                        last great sailing-ship captains, and the first frigate captain of the steam era."</quote></note>
               </person>
               <person>
                  <persName xml:id="Pratt">Archdeacon Pratt</persName>
                  <note>Excerpt from “Pratt, John Henry” by <bibl><author>Anita McConnell</author></bibl> for the <bibl><title>Oxford Dictionary of
                           National Biography</title></bibl>: <quote>“Pratt, John Henry (bap. 1809, d. 1871), Church of England clergyman and
                        mathematician, was baptized on 30 June 1809 at St Mary Woolnoth, London, one of two sons of Josiah Pratt (1768–1844), Church
                        of England clergyman, and his wife, Elizabeth, formerly Jowett. He was educated at Oakham School, Rutland, and entered
                        Gonville and Caius College, Cambridge, in 1829, graduating BA in 1833 as third wrangler. He was elected to a fellowship, and
                        proceeded MA in 1836. After taking orders he was appointed through the influence of Daniel Wilson, bishop of Calcutta, a
                        chaplain of the East India Company in 1838. He became Wilson's domestic chaplain and in 1850 archdeacon of
                     Calcutta.”</quote></note>
               </person>
               <person>
                  <persName xml:id="George_Horner">George Horner</persName>
                  <note>George Horner, a bandsman, joined the Chesapeake on August 12, 1857. He was born in London in 1817. The muster book for the
                     Chesapeake claims to offer the first entry for George Horner, perhaps meaning this was his first time at sea.<bibl>Muster Book of
                        Her Majesty's Ship Chesapeake Commencing 1st January 1858 Ending 31st March 1858, held by the National Archives at Kew (ADM
                        38/2884)</bibl></note>
               </person>
               <person>
                  <persName xml:id="Charles_Stewart">Charles Stewart</persName>
                  <note>Charles Stewart, an ordinary seaman, joined the Chesapeake on May 23, 1857. He was born in London and served aboard HMS
                     Gladiator just before joining the Chesapeake. He was born in 1834.<bibl>Muster Book of Her Majesty's Ship Chesapeake Commencing
                        1st January 1858 Ending 31st March 1858, held by the National Archives at Kew (ADM 38/2884)</bibl></note>
               </person>
               <person>
                  <persName xml:id="Thomas_Walsh">Thomas Walsh</persName>
                  <note>Thomas Walsh, an ordinary seaman, joined the Chesapeake on August 15, 1857. He was born in London in 1834 and served aboard
                     HMS Cressy just before joining the Chesapeake.<bibl>Muster Book of Her Majesty's Ship Chesapeake Commencing 1st January 1858
                        Ending 31st March 1858, held by the National Archives at Kew (ADM 38/2884)</bibl></note>
               </person>
               <person>
                  <persName xml:id="Robert_Wilkinson">Robert Wilkinson</persName>
                  <note>Robert Wilkinson, a private in the Royal Marines, joined the Chesapeake on July 25th 1857. He was born in Sitchfield,
                        Staffordshire.<bibl>Muster Book of Her Majesty's Ship Chesapeake Commencing 1st January 1858 Ending 31st March 1858, held by
                        the National Archives at Kew (ADM 38/2884)</bibl></note>
               </person>
               <person>
                  <persName xml:id="Henry_Underhill">Henry Underhill</persName>
                  <note>muster#153, ordinary seaman from Alesford, 36 when coming aboard the Chesapeake<bibl>Muster Book of Her Majesty's Ship
                        Chesapeake Commencing 1st January 1858 Ending 31st March 1858, held by the National Archives at Kew (ADM 38/2884)</bibl>
                  </note>
               </person>
               <person>
                  <persName xml:id="John_Welsh">John Welsh</persName>
                  <note>John Welsh, an ordinary seaman, joined the Chesapeake on February 20, 1857. He was born in Mayo<bibl>Muster Book of Her
                        Majesty's Ship Chesapeake Commencing 1st January 1858 Ending 31st March 1858, held by the National Archives at Kew (ADM
                        38/2884)</bibl></note>
               </person>
               <person>
                  <persName xml:id="Henry_Montagu">Henry Montagu</persName>
                  <note>Henry Montagu, yeoman of signals, joined the Chesapeake on July 28, 1857 after serving aboard HMS President. He was born in
                     St. Hilliers, Jersey (the Channel Islands) in 1826, making him 32 at the time of the performance.<bibl>Muster Book of Her
                        Majesty's Ship Chesapeake Commencing 1st January 1858 Ending 31st March 1858, held by the National Archives at Kew (ADM
                        38/2884)</bibl></note>
               </person>
               <person>
                  <persName xml:id="Isaac_Wright">Isaac Wright</persName>
                  <note>Isaac Wright, an ordinary sailor 2nd class, joined the Chesapeake on September 4th 1857. Hew as born in Sunderland in 1835,
                     making him 23 at the time of the performance.<bibl>Muster Book of Her Majesty's Ship Chesapeake Commencing 1st January 1858
                        Ending 31st March 1858, held by the National Archives at Kew (ADM 38/2884)</bibl></note>
               </person>
               <person>
                  <persName xml:id="Henry_Hamilton">Henry Hamilton</persName>
                  <note>C. R. B. Hamilton (the only Hamilton in the musters) was a naval cadet who served aboard <orgName ref="Colossus">HMS
                        Colossus</orgName> before joining the Chesapeake on July 23, 1857. He was born in County Tyrone, Ireland in December of 1842,
                     making him 15 at the time the performance<bibl>Muster Book of Her Majesty's Ship Chesapeake Commencing 1st January 1858 Ending
                        31st March 1858, held by the National Archives at Kew (ADM 38/2884)</bibl></note>
               </person>
               <person>
                  <persName xml:id="James_Brown">James Browne</persName>
                  <note>James Brown, an ordinary seaman, joined the Chesapeake on July 23, 1857, after serving aboard <orgName ref="Cuckoo">HMS
                        Cuckoo</orgName> until February 3, 1857. He was born at Sheerness on the 17th of January 1829, making him 28 at the time of
                     the performance<bibl>Muster Book of Her Majesty's Ship Chesapeake Commencing 1st January 1858 Ending 31st March 1858, held by the
                        National Archives at Kew (ADM 38/2884)</bibl></note>
               </person>
               <person>
                  <persName xml:id="William_Connell">William T Connell</persName>
                  <note>William T. Connell, an ordinary seaman, joined the Chesapeake on July 31 1857, after serving aboard <orgName ref="Eurydice"
                        >HMS Eurydice</orgName> until 17 June 1857. He was born in London in 1835, making him 27 at the time of the
                        performance.<bibl>Muster Book of Her Majesty's Ship Chesapeake Commencing 1st January 1858 Ending 31st March 1858, held by the
                        National Archives at Kew (ADM 38/2884)</bibl></note>
               </person>
               <person>
                  <persName xml:id="Taylor">Edward Taylor</persName>
                  <note>Edward Taylor, Assistant Engineer 3rd class (a commissioned officer), joined the Chesapeake on July 25th 1857. His age was not
                     recorded in the muster book<bibl>Muster Book of Her Majesty's Ship Chesapeake Commencing 1st January 1858 Ending 31st March 1858,
                        held by the National Archives at Kew (ADM 38/2884)</bibl></note>
               </person>
               <person>
                  <persName xml:id="Brownrigg">Charles J. Brownrigg</persName>
                  <note>Charles J. Brownrigg, a mate (a commissioned officer), joined the Chesapeake on August 4th, 1857. His age was not recorded in
                     the muster book.<bibl>Muster Book of Her Majesty's Ship Chesapeake Commencing 1st January 1858 Ending 31st March 1858, held by
                        the National Archives at Kew (ADM 38/2884)</bibl></note>
               </person>
               <person>
                  <persName xml:id="Wilkinson">Wilkinson</persName>
                  <note>Mr. Wilkinson, a clerk (a subordinate officer), joined the Chesapeake on July 23rd 1857 after serving aboard HMS Majestic. He
                     was born in Suffolk in 1836, which would make him 22 at the time of the cricket match in Calcutta<bibl>Muster Book of Her
                        Majesty's Ship Chesapeake Commencing 1st January 1858 Ending 31st March 1858, held by the National Archives at Kew (ADM
                        38/2884)</bibl></note>
               </person>
               <person>
                  <persName xml:id="Shortt">John Shortt</persName>
                  <note>John Shortt, a subordinate officer, joined the Chesapeake on July 23rd 1857, after serving aboard HMS Euridice. He was born in
                     Bombay in 1838, making him 20 at the time of this cricket match in Calcutta.<bibl>Muster Book of Her Majesty's Ship Chesapeake
                        Commencing 1st January 1858 Ending 31st March 1858, held by the National Archives at Kew (ADM 38/2884)</bibl></note>
               </person>
               <person>
                  <persName xml:id="Reynolds">S. Reynolds</persName>
                  <note>S. Reynolds, an ordinary seaman, joined the Chesapeake on September 4th 1857. He was born in Landport (Portsmouth) in 1839,
                     making him 19 at the time of the cricket match in Calcutta.<bibl>Muster Book of Her Majesty's Ship Chesapeake Commencing 1st
                        January 1858 Ending 31st March 1858, held by the National Archives at Kew (ADM 38/2884)</bibl></note>
               </person>
               <person>
                  <persName xml:id="Theobald">C.B. Theobald</persName>
                  <note>C.B. Theobald, a naval cadet, joined the Chesapeake on July 24th 1857. He was born in Mark's Tey, Essex in 1843, making him 15
                     at the time of the cricket match in Calcutta.<bibl>Muster Book of Her Majesty's Ship Chesapeake Commencing 1st January 1858
                        Ending 31st March 1858, held by the National Archives at Kew (ADM 38/2884)</bibl></note>
               </person>
               <person>
                  <persName xml:id="Cooper">Cooper</persName>
                  <note>There are three different members of the ship's company with the last name Cooper. The only thing we can tell about the
                     "Cooper" referenced in the cricket match is that he was not a commissioned officer, but an ordinary seaman.<bibl>Muster Book of
                        Her Majesty's Ship Chesapeake Commencing 1st January 1858 Ending 31st March 1858, held by the National Archives at Kew (ADM
                        38/2884)</bibl></note>
               </person>
               <person>
                  <persName xml:id="Chute">Charles T. Chute</persName>
                  <note>Charles T. Chute, a subordinate officer, joined the Chesapeake on July 23rd 1857, after serving aboard Euridice. He was born
                     in London in 1841, making him 17 at the time of the cricket match in Calcutta.<bibl>Muster Book of Her Majesty's Ship Chesapeake
                        Commencing 1st January 1858 Ending 31st March 1858, held by the National Archives at Kew (ADM 38/2884)</bibl></note>
               </person>
               <person>
                  <persName xml:id="Bew">James Bew</persName>
                  <note>James Bew, an experienced seaman, joined the Chesapeake on August 1st 1857. He was born in 1833, making him 25 at the time of
                     the cricket match in Calcutta.<bibl>Muster Book of Her Majesty's Ship Chesapeake Commencing 1st January 1858 Ending 31st March
                        1858, held by the National Archives at Kew (ADM 38/2884)</bibl></note>
               </person>
               <person>
                  <persName xml:id="Oxley">C.L. Oxley</persName>
                  <note>C.L. Oxley, a midshipman, joined the Chesapeake on July 29th 1857. He was born in 1841, making him 17 at the time of the
                     cricket match in Calcutta.<bibl>Muster Book of Her Majesty's Ship Chesapeake Commencing 1st January 1858 Ending 31st March 1858,
                        held by the National Archives at Kew (ADM 38/2884)</bibl></note>
               </person>
               <person>
                  <persName xml:id="Behadoor">Rajah Behadoor</persName>
                  <note>Still searching for biographical details on Rajah Behadoor</note>
               </person>
               <person>
                  <persName xml:id="Hope">Hope</persName>
                  <note>Hope played for the "squadron's eleven" and does not appear in Chesapeak muster book, which means he likely belonged to
                     another ship in the squadron<bibl>Muster Book of Her Majesty's Ship Chesapeake Commencing 1st January 1858 Ending 31st March
                        1858, held by the National Archives at Kew (ADM 38/2884)</bibl></note>
               </person>
               <person>
                  <persName xml:id="Haswell">Haswell</persName>
                  <note>Haswell served aboard Himalaya until he was injured and replaced by Piers.<bibl>Muster Book of Her Majesty's Ship Chesapeake
                        Commencing 1st January 1858 Ending 31st March 1858, held by the National Archives at Kew (ADM 38/2884)</bibl></note>
               </person>
               <person>
                  <persName xml:id="Kelly">Lieutenant Edward Kelly</persName>
                  <note>Lieutenant Edward Kelly does not appear in the muster book of HMS Chesapeake. <bibl>Muster Book of Her Majesty's Ship
                        Chesapeake Commencing 1st January 1858 Ending 31st March 1858, held by the National Archives at Kew (ADM
                     38/2884)</bibl></note>
               </person>
               <person>
                  <persName xml:id="Parkin">George H. Parkin</persName>
                  <note>George H. Parkin was named acting commander of HMS Chesapeake on February 1st 1858 and came aboard on February 25th after
                     serving aboard Roebuck. <bibl>Muster Book of Her Majesty's Ship Chesapeake Commencing 1st January 1858 Ending 31st March 1858,
                        held by the National Archives at Kew (ADM 38/2884)</bibl></note>
               </person>
               <person>
                  <persName xml:id="Piers">S.B. Piers</persName>
                  <note>S.B. Piers, a commander, joined the Chesapeake on July 28th 1857. He was discharged on January 22nd 1858 to serve aboard HMS
                     Himalaya when vice Haswell was invalided.<bibl>Muster Book of Her Majesty's Ship Chesapeake Commencing 1st January 1858 Ending
                        31st March 1858, held by the National Archives at Kew (ADM 38/2884)</bibl></note>
               </person>
               <person>
                  <persName xml:id="Namik_Pacha">Namik Pacha</persName>
                  <note>cite one of the articles on the uprising</note>
               </person>
            </listPerson>
            <listOrg>
               <org>
                  <orgName xml:id="Pelorus">Pelorus</orgName>
                  <note>HMS Pelorus was a Royal Navy screw corvette with twenty-one guns in the Pearl class. She was launched on February 5, 1858 and
                     her masting and fitting-out was completed on September 10, 1857. She was 200 feet long, 40 feet 4 inches at the broadest point,
                     with a depth in the hold of 23 feet 11 inches. As Lyon and Winfield explain, "Corvette designs were rapidly enlarged over the
                     1860s, as the corvette began to take over the traditional role of policing the high seas. To this end they were all built as
                     steam auxiliaries, designed to cruise under sail" (207). HMS Pelorus was broken up for parts at Devonport on February 3, 1869.
                     David Lyon and Rif Winfield, The Sail &amp; Steam Navy List: All the Ships of the Royal Navy, 1815–1889 (London: Chatham
                     Publishing), 2004.</note>
               </org>
               <org>
                  <orgName xml:id="Roebuck">Roebuck</orgName>
                  <note>HMS Roebuck was a Royal Navy despatch vessel with 5 guns in the Intrepid class. She was launched on March 22, 1856 and her
                     masting and fitting-out was completed on August 25, 1857. She was 200 feet long, 179 feet 5 1/4 inches at the broadest point,
                     with a depth in the hold of 14 feet 6 inches. She was built for a company of 100 men. As Lyon and Winfield explain, "The outbreak
                     of the Russian War demonstrated the need for numerous manoeuvrable, shallow-draught vessels for coastal and inshore operations in
                     the Baltic and Black Seas. Six small screw steamers of the Arrow Class were approved to be built by contract in the Thames [...]"
                     (218). The Roebuck was one of twenty additional vessels ordered in 1855 (218-219). David Lyon and Rif Winfield, The Sail &amp;
                     Steam Navy List: All the Ships of the Royal Navy, 1815–1889 (London: Chatham Publishing), 2004.</note>
               </org>
               <org>
                  <orgName xml:id="Cyclops">Cyclops</orgName>
                  <note>HMS Cyclops was a Royal Navy steam vessel with six guns in the Cyclops class. She was launched on July 10, 1839. She was 190
                     feet 3 inches long, 163 feet 6 inches at the broadest point, with a depth in the hold of 37 feet 6 inches. She was built for a
                     company of 175 to 200 men. As Lyon and Winfield explain, the ship was re-armed in 1856 "with 2x 68 pdrds (95cwt) on the pivots
                     and 4 x 10in (84cwt) on the broadside trucks." They also explain that she "was fitted 1856/57 to assist with the laying of the
                     Atlantic cable (151). David Lyon and Rif Winfield, The Sail &amp; Steam Navy List: All the Ships of the Royal Navy, 1815–1889
                     (London: Chatham Publishing), 2004. </note>
               </org>
               <org>
                  <orgName xml:id="Chesapeake">Chesapeake</orgName>
                  <note>HMS Chesapeake was a Royal Navy screw frigate with fifty-one guns in the Forte (or Imperieuse) class, which was one of several
                     classes including the thirty new wooden screw frigates completed between 1849 and 1865 (197). She was built in dry dock, launched
                     on September 7, 1855, and her masting and fitting-out was completed on August 28, 1857. She was 212 feet long, 50 feet 2 inches
                     at the broadest point, with a depth in the hold of 16 feet and 9 inches. She was built for a company of 515 men. The Chesapeake
                     was sold in 1867 to be broken up for parts at Charlton (200). David Lyon and Rif Winfield, The Sail &amp; Steam Navy List: All
                     the Ships of the Royal Navy, 1815–1889 (London: Chatham Publishing), 2004.</note>
               </org>
            </listOrg>
         </particDesc>
      </profileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>column breaks have not been retained, superscript has not been retained. Individual paragraphs have not been captured, making it seem
               like an entire contribution is one complete paragraph, which is not the case. Only the beginning of most contributions have been
               transcribed, followed by [...] indicating additional content to be transcribed. Where there is no title, "No Title" is used as the
               header.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <pb n="IMG_0286" facs="https://farm2.staticflickr.com/1740/40668620790_f4ce895caa_k_d.jpg"/>
         <div n="42" type="issue">
            <head type="main">"The Young Idea"</head>
            <head type="main">Chesapeake Chronicle and Weekly Journal</head>
            <head type="sub">Saturday 20th November 1858</head>
            <head type="sub">Vol 1. No 42</head>
            <div type="article">
               <head>No Title</head>
               <p> Our stay at Jeddah has worn a very monotonous aspect. Strangers, to the shore, we have only been able to gaze from our bulwarks on
                  the far spreading sands, and barren hills of Arabia, and sigh to don the garment of some Mecca pilgrim, mount on the hump of some
                  fleet camel, and all Christian as we are, penetrate into the holiest shrines, and sanctuaries of Islam. [...]<pb n="TYI1422"/>[...]
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="article">
               <head>Sailing up the Red Sea.</head>
               <p>Sunday Morning 17 Octr. Having sailed with a fair breeze from Aden yesterday afternoon, we are this morning in sight of the straits
                  of Babel-Mandel. [...details the ship approaching Jeddah with the help of a Arab pilot named Abdullah...] <pb n="TYI1423"/>[...]</p>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <head>Tuesday 19 Octr 1858</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>The sun had past his highest point, the sea was calm &amp; bright</l>
                  <l>The ship was slowly urged along, by breezes soft and light</l>
                  <l>[...9 quatrains of verse describing a shark eating a midshipman's jacket and then being caught and eaten by the crew]</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="article">
               <head>The Late Comet.</head>
               <p>We are sorry that the very brief notes taken by "our own Observer", will not permit us to give any elaborate or scientific account
                  of this beautiful heavenly visitor. It was on the Evening of Septr 30th after dropping anchor at Aden, that our attention was first
                  called to see the bright stranger, which had made its appearance, unpredicted, &amp; unannounced among the celestial bodies of the
                  Northern Hemisphere.[...]<pb n="TYI1424"/>[...]</p>
            </div>
            <div type="Naval_Intelligence">
               <head>Naval Intelligence</head>
               <p>22nd Octr. H.M.S. Chesapeake arrived at Jeddah on Friday 22nd at 5 P.M. having been piloted in through the outer reefs by Mr Mayes
                  Master of the Cyclops. [...]</p>
            </div>
            <div type="Epitome">
               <head>Epitome</head>
               <p>On Monday Oct 25 preparations were made for the reception of His Excellency Nemuk Pacha, and the English &amp; French Commissioners,
                  but his Excellency being indiscposed after visiting the "<orgName ref="#Pelorus">Pelorus</orgName>" was unable to visit us. The
                  Commissioners however came on board and inspected the ship.[...general reports of storms and boredom]</p>
            </div>
            <div type="Facetiae">
               <head>Facetiae</head>
               <p>A shocking punster, hearing that Jeddah was celebrated for Turquoise, said that if Turks &amp; Arabs were on unfriendly terms, no
                  doubt plenty of "Turk Wars" would be the result. [...other puns]</p>
            </div>
            <div type="Enigma">
               <head>Enigma</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>Bone on the wing of yon dark plumag'd bird</l>
                  <l>High o'er the earth how oft I took my flight:[...three quatrains of a riddle]</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="Answer_Rebus">
               <head/>
               <lg>
                  <l>!Tis the Emerald Isle where the rough jaunting "car".</l>
                  <l>Will bear you in country or town [in verse explaining that the answer is "carnation"]</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="Publication_Information">
               <head>The Young Idea</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>Published at the office No 1 POrt St Chesapeake, every Saturday[...]</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
         </div>
         <pb n="TYI1431"/>
         <div n="43" type="issue">
            <head type="main">"The Young Idea"</head>
            <head type="main">Chesapeake Chronicle and Weekly Journal</head>
            <head type="sub">Saturday 27th November 1858</head>
            <head type="sub">Vol 1. No 43</head>
            <div type="article">
               <head>No Title</head>
               <p>Our past week has produced one circumstance which had caused some little excitement amongst the squadron, and has for a short period
                  dispeled the monotony of our life; we refer to the race between our Barge and the "<orgName ref="#Pelorus">Pelorus</orgName>'s"
                     Cutter.[...]<pb n="TYI1432"/>[...]</p>
            </div>
            <div type="article">
               <head>Jeddah, our Visit to Namik Pacha.</head>
               <head type="sub">Tuesday 26 Octr 1858</head>
               <p>We left our ship, a large party of us, in three Boats at half past 8 a.m., and after various difficulties in avoiding coral rocks,
                  and crossing shoal Water, came alongside the Jetty near the Southern extremity of the Town. Here we perceived the KaimaKhan, or
                  Governor of Jeddah dressed in purple uniform coat, and attended by the Harbour Master in his suit of brown cloth, waiting to receive
                  us. He shook each one by the hand as we ascended the steps &amp; Passing under the gateway, found a number of Arab steeds in gay
                  trappings, &amp; saddles, ready for us to mount. We formed a brilliant cavalcade, as we set out on our progress thro' the town. We
                  were 20 in all, and all attired in our uniform frock coats &amp; swords with white flowing turbans encircling our caps. Captains
                  Pullen, and Parkin led the way, attended by the Kaima Khan, while we followed by twos and threes, and well armed Turkish attendants,
                  Bashi Bazouks we believe with plenty of silver mounted pistols at their girdles welked at our horses heads. After passing an open
                  space in which loungers were sitting smoking hookahs, and drinking coffee, &amp; camels lying wiht piles of goods around them, our
                  road lay thro' the long winding streets of the Bazaars, where articles of every description were exposed for Sale, &amp; human faces
                  of every shape and color met the view. There was so much novelty to attract the eye; that it was difficult to notice anything
                  occurately. The Bazaars were so narrow that two horsemen could with difficulty ride abreast, without pushing against the wares on
                  either side. In some parts swarms of flies rendered our progress annoying. There were broad vessels piled up with dates, or melons,
                  or pomegranates, or oranges; trays on which large broad cakes, or other eatables were exposed for sale. shops in which the porous
                  water coolers, and other simple earthenwares were hangingin, or silks and muslins of various kinds, or strings of breads, amber
                  black or white coral or cornelian, such as devout Musselmen use in prayer, or Turkish slippers; or long pipes and outhpieces; all
                  whihc for a moment only caught the eye as our steeds passed on. The human faces most attracted us, the light hughed caucasian
                  features of the Turk., the well bronzed countenance of the native Arab the broad Ethiopian visage of the black slave, the veiled
                  face of some female, <choice>
                     <orig>here</orig>
                     <corr>her</corr>
                  </choice> eyes only peering thro' the white muslin "yek-mesh", the scowling gaze of the wild Bedouin as he stood erect in his
                  uncleanly brown robe, his head enveloped in a cowl, with his hand ready at the [...interesting exchange about tobacco as snuff, with
                  Pasha saying it was "good for the gums" and his inquiries about the men in black, who it turns out where the chaplains, described by
                  Parkin as "the two professors who instructed the youths in theology &amp; navigation"...will continue in next number]</p>
            </div>
            <div type="sporting_intelligence">
               <head type="main">SPORTING INTELLIGENCE</head>
               <head type="sub">Boat Race between the Chesapeakes Barge and <orgName ref="#Pelorus">Pelorus</orgName>'s Cutter.></head>
               <p>[...]</p>
            </div>
            <div type="song">
               <head type="main">(Song)</head>
               <head type="main">The Cheasapeake's Barge</head>
               <head type="sub">Air (Yankee doodle)</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>of the "Chesapeake's of old,</l>
                  <l>[...]</l>
                  <pb n="?????"/>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="Article">
               <head>Namik Pacha, &amp; the Merchants of Jeddah</head>
               <p>It is said that Namik Pacha being fearful that the rich Merchants of Jeddah would remove their wealth at the sight of our English
                  ships, invited them to a friendly entertainment, and in true Eastern spirit then detained them in safe custody. eleven in number. We
                  hear also that the new Sheriff has in a similar way detained several at Mecca, with the view of procuring from them the fine which
                  is supposed will be exacted by the English and French Governments</p>
            </div>
            <div type="Epitome">
               <head type="main">Epitome</head>
               <head type="sub">Festivities in the Ward room.</head>
               <p>On Wednesday Evening 25th Inst several officers from "Cyclops" and "<orgName ref="#Pelorus">Pelorus</orgName>" assembled on board
                  the "Chesapeake" and after much merry dancing while the Band was playing on the Main Deck, retired to the Ward room to finish the
                  Evening with a bowl of punch, and a few concomitant songs [more details about celebrations and such...]</p>
            </div>
            <div type="Facetiae">
               <head>Facetiae</head>
               <p>[...]</p>
            </div>
            <div type="rebus">
               <head>Rebus</head>
               <p>[...]</p>
            </div>
            <div type="Publication_Info">
               <head>The Young Idea</head>
               <p>[...]</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <pb n="TYI1441"/>
         <div n="44" type="issue">
            <head type="main">"The Young Idea"</head>
            <head type="main">Chesapeake Chronicle and Weekly Journal</head>
            <head type="sub">Saturday 4th December 1858</head>
            <head type="sub">Vol 1. No 44</head>
            <div type="article">
               <head>No Title</head>
               <p>[...]</p>
            </div>
            <div type="article">
               <head>Jeddah, and our Visit to Namik Pacha</head>
               <head type="sub">continued from last week</head>
               <p>[...]<pb n="TYI1442"/>[...]</p>
            </div>
            <div type="sporting_intelligence">
               <head>SPORTING INTELLIGENCE</head>
               <p>[...]</p>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <head>The Editor of The "Young Idea" to his friends on closing the first Year of Publication.</head>
               <p>[...]<pb n="TYI1443"/>[...]</p>
            </div>
            <div type="published_elsewhere">
               <head>The Red Sea</head>
               <p>[...]</p>
            </div>
            <div type="Naval_Intelligence">
               <head>Naval Intelligence</head>
               <p>[...]<pb n="TYI1444"/>[...]</p>
            </div>
            <div type="epitome">
               <head>Epitome</head>
               <p>[...]</p>
            </div>
            <div type="facetiae">
               <head>Facetiae</head>
               <p>[...]</p>
            </div>
            <div type="Conundrums">
               <head>Conundrums</head>
               <p>[...]</p>
            </div>
            <div type="publication_info">
               <head>The Young Idea</head>
               <p>[...]</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <pb n="TYI2011"/>
         <div n="1" type="issue">
            <head type="main">"The Young Idea"</head>
            <head type="main">Chesapeake Chronicle and Weekly Journal</head>
            <head type="sub">Saturday 18th December 1858</head>
            <head type="sub">Vol 2. An accident to the Editor prevented last weeks no. from appearing No 1.</head>
            <div type="article">
               <head>No Title</head>
               <p>[...]</p>
            </div>
            <div type="article">
               <head>A visit to the Sheriffe of Mecca</head>
               <p>[...]<pb n="TYI2012"/></p>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <head>From the Readers to the Editor on commencing his New Volume</head>
               <p>[...]</p>
            </div>
            <pb n="TYI2013"/>
            <div type="article">
               <head>The Tricolor and Union Jack</head>
               <p>[...socializing between British and French sailors]</p>
            </div>
            <div type="song">
               <head>Christmas 1858</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>[...]<pb n="TYI2014"/>[...]</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="article">
               <head>The Garbarry</head>
               <p>[...interesting story of assisting a ship that got stuck on the reef. Parkin assisted and the Du Chayle sent a boat as well...when
                  the job was done some of the men drank too much]</p>
            </div>
            <div type="Naval_Intelligence">
               <head>Naval Intelligence</head>
               <p>[...]</p>
            </div>
            <div type="epitome">
               <head>Epitome</head>
               <p>[...]</p>
            </div>
            <div type="facetiae">
               <head>Facetiae</head>
               <p>[...]</p>
            </div>
            <div type="rebus">
               <head>Rebus</head>
               <p>[...]</p>
            </div>
            <div type="answers">
               <head>Answers to Conundrums Nos. 60 &amp; 61</head>
               <p>[...]</p>
            </div>
            <div type="publication_info">
               <head>The Young Idea</head>
               <p>[...]</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <pb n="TYI2021"/>
         <div n="2" type="issue">
            <head type="main">"The Young Idea"</head>
            <head type="main">Chesapeake Chronicle and Weekly Journal</head>
            <head type="sub">Saturday 25th December 1858</head>
            <head type="sub">Vol 2. No 2.</head>
            <div type="article">
               <head>No Title</head>
               <p>[...]</p>
            </div>
            <pb n="TYI2022"/>
            <div type="poem">
               <head>Chesapeake's Greeting to "<orgName ref="#Pelorus">Pelorus</orgName></head>
               <lg>
                  <l>We've pull'd and we've sail'd together</l>
                  <l>[...]</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="rough_yarns">
               <head>Rough Yarns No 1. "The Boutswains Christmas Dinner"</head>
               <p>[...] <pb n="TYI2023"/>[...]</p>
            </div>
            <div type="epitome">
               <head>Epitome</head>
               <p>[...]</p>
            </div>
            <div type="facetiae">
               <head>Facetiae</head>
               <p>[...]</p>
            </div>
            <pb n="TYI2024"/>
            <div type="illustration">
               <head>[...]</head>
               <p>[...]</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <pb n="TYI2031"/>
         <div n="3" type="issue">
            <head type="main">"The Young Idea"</head>
            <head type="main">Chesapeake Chronicle and Weekly Journal</head>
            <head type="sub">Saturday 1st January 1859</head>
            <head type="sub">Vol 2. No 3.</head>
            <div type="article">
               <head>No Title</head>
               <p>[...]</p>
            </div>
            <pb n="TYI2032"/>
            <div type="article">
               <head>Christmas Day 1858</head>
               <p>[...]</p>
            </div>
            <div type="article">
               <head>Farewell Dinner to Capt Parkin</head>
               <p>[...]<pb n="TYI2033" facs="https://farm2.staticflickr.com/1754/40668619260_625db61c72_k_d.jpg"/>[...]</p>
            </div>
            <div type="article">
               <head>Our Christmas Play</head>
               <p>Our Christmas play came off in right merry style on Wednesday Evening (29 Decr). Our quarter deck, roofed in with flags of all
                  nations, presented as gay a Theatre as one would wish to see, while the rising tiers of benches from the deck to the bridge abaft,
                  accommodated a large and happy audience, not only of our own bluejackets, but of those from the "<orgName ref="#Pelorus"
                     >Pelorus</orgName>", the "DuChayla" and the "Roebuck".</p>
               <p>We are proud of our Amateur Performers, who have this time surpassed themselves. The comedy of King Charles the SEcond" being cast
                  as on the last occasion, we need say little, except to compliment the fair "Mary" the Wapping beauty, around whom the whole plot
                  clusters, on the increasing ease, &amp; freedome with which she plays her part. "Charles" was as royal, "Rochester" as Manly, and
                  old "Copp" as jolly hearted as ever.</p>
               <p>The two farces which follwed kept the audience in a state of continuoual laughter and applause. Thos Walsh, as "Paddy Carey" was
                  indeed a "broth of a boy", speaking with a rich brogue, whirling his shillelah in true Hibernian spirit, touching the hearts of the
                  audience by the generous<pb n="TYI2034" facs="https://farm2.staticflickr.com/1743/27606331227_4931573b8b_k_d.jpg"/>nature of the
                  deeds represented, and winding up with a song, and a "jig" which brought down thunders of applause. The other characters of the
                  piece were all good, but "widow Leary" the landlady deserves special mention. She was the yielding widow, and the Irish landlady is
                  perfection.</p>
               <p>In the "Man about Town" the chief burden of the piece rested upon Isaac Wright as "Skirts", and well did he sustain it. Coming in
                  which his two large placards of the "Learned PIg," he at once moved our mucles to a state of risibility, which we found it difficult
                  to pause from, such was the continued succession of funny deeds, and speeches. Horner as "Dr Mandible" the physician Walsh as
                  "Topps" the Tiger, and indeed all the minor characters, played up to him well, and the curtain fell amidst loud and long
                  applause.</p>
               <p>We may safely say that all Oficers &amp; men present, whether French or English, were delighted with their Evening's amusement, and
                  we were glad to observe our newly arrived Commodore, tho' rather late or the first piece, thoroughly enjoying the fun of the two
                  Farces.</p>
               <p>A supper was laid out on the Main Deck after the performance; for the Amateurs</p>
            </div>
            <div type="article">
               <head>A Night Alarm</head>
               <p>[...]</p>
            </div>
            <div type="naval_intelligence">
               <head>Naval Intelligence</head>
               <p>[...]</p>
            </div>
            <div type="answer">
               <head>Answer to Rebus in No 1</head>
               <p>[...]</p>
            </div>
            <div type="publication_info">
               <head>The Young Idea</head>
               <p>[...]</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <pb n="TYI2041"/>
         <div n="4" type="issue">
            <head type="main">"The Young Idea"</head>
            <head type="main">Chesapeake Chronicle and Weekly Journal</head>
            <head type="sub">Saturday 8th January 1859</head>
            <head type="sub">Vol 2. No 4.</head>
            <div type="article">
               <head>No Title</head>
               <p>[...]</p>
            </div>
            <pb n="TYI2042"/>
            <div type="previously_published">
               <head>Notes about Mecca (from Sale's Koran)</head>
               <p>[...]</p>
            </div>
            <div type="article">
               <head>"Jack</head>
               <p>[...]<pb n="TYI2043"/>[...]</p>
            </div>
            <div type="song">
               <head>Song on the Death of Capt. Sir William Peel KCB R.N.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>[...]</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="article">
               <head>Sand Squalls &amp; Rain Squalls</head>
               <p>[...]<pb n="TYI2044"/>[...]</p>
            </div>
            <div type="naval_intelligence">
               <head>Naval Intelligence</head>
               <p>[...]</p>
            </div>
            <div type="epitome">
               <head>Epitome</head>
               <p>[...]</p>
            </div>
            <div type="rebus">
               <head>Rebus</head>
               <p>[...]</p>
            </div>
            <div type="advertisement">
               <head>Cheseapeake Amateur Theatricals</head>
               <p>[...requesting funding from voluntary contributions]</p>
            </div>
            <div type="answers">
               <head>Answer to Pictorial Rebus in No 3 Vol 2</head>
               <p>[...]</p>
            </div>
            <div type="publication_info">
               <head>The Young Idea</head>
               <p>[...]</p>
            </div>
            <pb n="TYI2051" facs="https://farm2.staticflickr.com/1724/27606330737_ca86ec2427_k_d.jpg"/>
            <div n="5" type="issue">
               <head type="main">"The Young Idea"</head>
               <head type="main">Chesapeake Chronicle and Weekly Journal</head>
               <head type="sub">Saturday 15th January 1859</head>
               <head type="sub">Vol 2. No 5.</head>
               <div type="article">
                  <head>No Title</head>
                  <p>A tardy act of justice has at length been accomplished, and two of the prime instigators of the "Jeddah Massacre" have paid with
                     their lives the penalty of their murderous deed. We know not who may have been those Eleven wretched Arabs, who on a former
                     occasion were executed on the reefs in the sight of the "Cyclops"; but at all events they were but the tools, the instruments of
                     the crime; the origin of it has been clearly traced home to the three chief men in Jeddah, those whose duty it was to protect,
                     and defend the Christians, and strangers who felt secure in their friends help.</p>
                  <p>Horrible as was the sight of blood on Wednesday morning, we must rejoice as Englishmen, that justice has found out its true
                     victims; the third guilty man, the late Kaima Khan of Jeddah, is, we hear to be sent to Constantinople, to await the Sultan's
                     decree, &amp; tho' we have sipped his coffee, &amp; smoked his pipes, we can scarcely regret that he too should meet with a like
                     fate. To the firmness of the French Commissioner, we believe this act of just retriubution may be attributed. Bombardment or the
                        execu<pb n="TYI2052" facs="https://farm2.staticflickr.com/1729/27606327217_e263448a59_k_d.jpg"/>tion of the guilty men were
                     the only alternatives offered, and Namik Pacha, at the last moment, with grief &amp; reluctance signed their death warrant.</p>
                  <p>We may now perhaps consider that the first great objects of the Jeddah Commission, &amp; of our own visit here, has been
                     accomplished, &amp; tho we hear that much still remains to be settled, in the way of indemnification, yet we would indulge a hope
                     that the presence of the Chesapeake may be no longer necessary. This very morning, the "Duchayla" has spread her wings again, and
                     is now speeding on her way to Suez tho', we believe to return again: let us hope that soon we may have to record how the
                     "Chesapeake" also has let fall her long-furled canvass, &amp; is far on her way to Aden &amp; the waters of the East.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="letter">
                  <head type="main">The Jeddah Massacre</head>
                  <head type="sub">Execution of Mahtesil and Amoudi.</head>
                  <floatingText>
                     <body>
                        <opener>To the Editor of the "Young Idea"<lb/>Dear Sir,</opener>
                        <p>As one of those whose duty it was to witness the Execution on Wednesday last (12th), I beg to send you some slight account
                           of what took place, tho' indeed I write even now with a feeling of horror at the spectacle At 4 am, as you know, we were
                           all astir, coffee being served out to the Marines and Boats' crews who were to attend. At One Bell we shoved off from the
                           ship, and it still wanted some time to daylight when we mustered, under Captain SEymour's orders, abreast of the old
                           Turkish hulk whihc is lying off the town. The "<orgName ref="#Pelorus">Pelorus</orgName>"' Boats were there and those of
                           the "Ducayla" a goodly squadron in all, three Pinnaces, besides several cutters, and two or three light gigs. The Pinnaces
                           each carried their brass gun in the bows, and all the Boat's crews were well provided with arms, and ammunition in case of
                           any sudden outbreak of the natives. As daylight broke over the walls and minarets of Jeddah, and the more distant hills
                           that bound our landscape to the Eastward, we started from our "rendezvous," the execution being fixed by the Turkish
                           authorities for one hour after daybreak. The Frenchmen led the way, the Boats following one another in single file; it took
                           us fully half an hour to reach the shore, the pilotage among the shoals being diffuclt, and by the time that all
                           arrangments were complete, the "one hour after daybreak" was fast expiring. We found the Turkish guard already drawn up at
                           the scene of execution; it was the square plot of ground on the Custom House Wharf, open to the shipping, and close under
                           the seawall of the town. As we stood facing the sea, the right side of the square was occupied by a company of Turkish
                           soldiers, perhaps 100 in number, a similar company of Albanians occupied the left; while a third side was formed of the
                           English Marines &amp; French Sailors, each fifty in nuber, with their backs against the wall of the town. The French
                           occupied theright of our position, their right thus touching the plank of the Turks, and between us waved, side by side,
                           the flags of our two countries, those flags which had been dishonoured, &amp;<pb n="TYI2053"
                              facs="https://farm2.staticflickr.com/1755/40668618580_b0b4e0fdab_k_d.jpg"/>insulted on that fearful night of the
                           Christian massacre. It wasa picturesque sight, though we stood in shadow, there were the Turks in their red Fez caps, dark
                           brown jackets, with red pipings and black accoutrements, muskets with long shining barrels, the men themselves of fair
                           height but somewhat dingy, and dirty looking. There were the Albanians, light in hue, tall and dressed in white, white
                           jacket, and white loose trousers, white cap with tassel, white ose, white bells, a red sas only relieving the unmixed white
                           of their costume; there werre our own in their blue and red Tunics (for half were Artillery, and half Light Infantry), and
                           their white forage caps; there were the French Sailors, in their blue jackets, and white trousers with red sash, and straw
                           sailors hat, armed with rifle and sword bayonet, while on the seaside, completing the square, were drawn up a single line
                           of Bashi Bazouks &amp; irregular Albanians, dressed in a strange variety of costume armed to the teeth with pistols,
                           swords, daggers, and knives, and of every hue &amp; shade of complexion, some jet black, others light, and fair. Behind all
                           were seen our boats, with their respective crews moored in line a boat's length from the shore, their sterns towards the
                           Quay</p>
                        <p>Our attention was now turned to a gateway in that corner of the Square on which the right of the Albanians rested. It was
                           the gateway leading into the town, adorned with open partico, that projected into the square. From this, as soon as we had
                           formed, guards were despatched to bring in the two prisoners. Everything was still; no inhabitants of the town were to be
                           seen or heard, except the few Turkish Officials who stood on the town wall behind us, or looked from the windows of a house
                           that commanded the Square. All approaches to the spot were closed, and guarded by Turkish sentries </p>
                        <p>But see!!! the prosoners approach and on them every eye is fixed.</p>
                        <p>The first one who entered is an old man thin, and spare, dressed in light green robe flowing to the feet, and white turban;
                           his beard white with age, his eye keen and piercing. His hands were tied behind, above the elbows, and he is attended by a
                           guard on either side, and a third behind; he halts on entering the square, and looks astonished. I can well believe the
                           story that is told that he knew not his approaching fate till that moment he casts his eyes around, and as they rest on our
                           "colours" he seems to comprehend all, and gives himself up to prayer. He is followed at a short interval by the other
                           prisoner, similarly guarded; a taller and apparently a younger man, with robe of dark purple, and white Turban; his hands
                           similarly tied, he is we understand the sheikh of that Arab trine which committed the massacre, while the older man is the
                           h"Chief of Bazaars" the richest and most powerful man in Jeddah. AS they seem to hesitate by the gateway, they are pushed
                           on by the guard into the cenre of the square and there they are compelled to kneel down with their faces turned Eastward,
                           towards Mecca. The guards retire, the executioners take their place with sword drawn; wild looking fellows, irregular
                           Albanians, their arms bare to the elbow, their sashes loaded wiht pistols. The old man is the first to suffer: as he bends
                           his head forward, the executioner seems to try his distance carefully with the sword, two or three times; -yet his first
                           blow strikes too low down the back: again the sword is raised, adn the blow falls on the neck but does not enter deeply;
                           the old man who is still murmering in prayer, turns his head, as though reproachfully; a third blow is struck, and he falls
                           forward on his face; the gush of blood seems to choke his utterance: his last words of prayer, gurgle out with his
                           lifeblood, but the head is not yet severed; it is butcher's work that follows: the remaining flesh is sawn through with the
                           sword, and the head rolled away from the body: a pool of blood rushed out upon the ground, the executioner lifts the robe
                           of the deceased, and wipes in it his sword and bloodstained fingers.</p>
                        <p>I could look no longer: a sickening sensation came over me: one of the French Sailors, a powerful man, fainted away: I saw
                           not the second execution; the gleam only of a decending sword seemed to flash before my eyes, and in another moment, I
                           heared that all was over: the head of the second prisoner had been severed at a single blow.</p>
                        <pb n="TYI2054"/>
                        <p>The Turkish authorities now advanced and flung over each of the bodies a white sheet; but this made the seem almost more
                           ghastly than before, for you could see the blood spouting from the arteries against the underside of the sheet, and with
                           each gush dying it afresh.</p>
                        <p>I was only too glad when the order was given to leave this scene of blood &amp; reembark in our boats. I am sure that not
                           one of those who saw it woudl ever with to witness such another scene</p>
                        <p>Captain Seymour, H.M.S. "<orgName ref="#Pelorus">Pelorus</orgName>" commanded our force, and was present inside the Square,
                           attended by the Commodore's Secretary and an Aide-de-camp, while Capt Tricault of "Duchayla" remained in charge of the boat
                           squadron.</p>
                        <closer>I remain Dear Sir<lb/>Yours truly</closer>
                        <signed>"Eye Witness"</signed>
                     </body>
                  </floatingText>
               </div>
               <div type="poem">
                  <head>Jeddah.</head>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Ah! Jeddah's towers are gleaming bright</l>
                     <l>[...]</l>
                  </lg>
               </div>
               <div type="naval_intelligence">
                  <head>Naval Intelligence</head>
                  <p>[...]</p>
               </div>
               <div type="epitome">
                  <head>Epitome</head>
                  <p>[...]</p>
                  <p>Peeping under a screen erected on the main deck, we have ascertained the creation of several new scenes, at which two or three
                     hands were busily paining. We anticipate much pleasure from the production of a new play on our arrival at Aden</p>
               </div>
               <div type="rebus">
                  <head>Rebus</head>
                  <p>[...]</p>
               </div>
               <div type="publication_info">
                  <head>"The Young Idea"</head>
                  <p>[...]</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <pb n="TYI2061" facs="https://farm2.staticflickr.com/1733/27606330287_1fc7c08300_k_d.jpg"/>
            <div n="6" type="issue">
               <head type="main">"The Young Idea"</head>
               <head type="main">Chesapeake Chronicle and Weekly Journal</head>
               <head type="sub">Saturday 29th January 1859</head>
               <head type="sub">Vol 2. No 6.</head>
               <div type="article">
                  <head>No Title</head>
                  <p>Only the total absence of all circumstances of note, has for a while, caused our weekly sheet to remain unstained with ink; our
                     pen to be useuless on the desk before us. "The Young Idea" professes to record events, not to invent fiction; but here at Jeddah
                     the record of one day, is a history of the whole: nothing has occurred to vary our monotony, except the hasty visit of our little
                     messenger the "Roebuck."</p>
                  <p>WE could almost envy them the fitful way in which they flit from place to place, pausing only for a day, or two at each station;
                     from Jeddah to Suez, or from Aden to Jeddah: they have shivered for a while in the real winter's cold of Egypt; they have
                     wandered through the Oriental Streets, and Bazaars of crowded Cairo; they have gazed on the green valley of the fertilizing Nile;
                     they have climbed to the summit of the Great Pyramid, and penetrated into its close, and half suffocating chambers, and we, all
                     the while, have been idly lying amongst the reefs of Jeddah, our minds gleaning no fresh idea from scenes before us, but
                     wandering vacantly into the future or the past.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="letter">
                  <head>Arabic Numberals</head>
                  <floatingText>
                     <body>
                        <opener>Dear Sir,</opener>
                        <p>It is well known how much European civilization owes to the influence of<pb n="TYI2062"/>the Arabian mind [...]</p>
                        <closer>Dear Sir, Yours very sincerely</closer>
                        <signed>Arithmeticus</signed>
                     </body>
                  </floatingText>
               </div>
               <div type="letter">
                  <head>Arabic Numberals</head>
                  <floatingText>
                     <body>
                        <opener>To the Editor of the "Young Idea"<lb/>Dear Sir</opener>
                        <p>I must call your attention to mistakes which are frequently made in our Rebuses [...]</p>
                        <closer>I remain<lb/>Yours very truly</closer>
                        <signed>"Sphynx"</signed>
                     </body>
                  </floatingText>
                  <p>Ed. We regret exceedingly [...] careless of our "devil."</p>
               </div>
               <div type="previously_published">
                  <head>More Notes about Mecca. <lb/>(chiefly from Sale's Koran).</head>
                  <p>[...]<pb n="TYI2063"/>[...]</p>
               </div>
               <div type="enigma">
                  <head>Historical Enigmas<lb/>No. 1</head>
                  <p>[...]<pb n="TYI2064" facs="https://farm2.staticflickr.com/1742/27606329597_eaa576cf96_k_d.jpg"/>[...]</p>
               </div>
               <div type="letter">
                  <head>The last New Riddle from England.</head>
                  <floatingText>
                     <body>
                        <opener>To the Editor of the Yg Idea<lb/>Dear Sir</opener>
                        <p>[...]</p>
                        <closer>I have the honor to be, Sir<lb/>Yours sincerely,</closer>
                        <signed>"Sphynx"</signed>
                     </body>
                  </floatingText>
               </div>
               <div type="naval_intelligence">
                  <head>Naval Intelligence</head>
                  <p>[...]</p>
               </div>
               <div type="epitome">
                  <head>Epitome.</head>
                  <p>[...]On Monday (24th) when shifting Topsails Isaac Wright Ordy fell backwards from the main Topsail Yard, but was happily brought
                     up by his knife lanyard hitching, whihc gave him time to grasp the rigging: we should indeed have been very sorry had anything
                     more serious befallen one, whose comic powers have so lately given us amusement</p>
                  <p>[...]</p>
                  <p>The three Arab dhouws with coal from Aden arrived on Wednesday (26) evening, &amp; we coaled that night, and the two succeeding
                     days.</p>
                  <p>Much amusement was caused in the Ward Room on Wednesday EVening, by the presence of a Messenger from the Pacha of Hoeidah to
                     Namik Pacha (a passenger in one of the Dhows) whose astonishment at various tricks with cards was of the most grotesque
                     description.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="facetiae">
                  <head>Facetiae.</head>
                  <p>A remark being made on the long line of "dhows" lying off Jeddah, [...]</p>
               </div>
               <div type="rebus">
                  <head>REBUS</head>
                  <p>[...]</p>
               </div>
               <div type="answer">
                  <head>Answer to Rebus in No. 5. Expostulation.</head>
               </div>
               <div type="publication_info">
                  <head>"The Young Idea"</head>
                  <p>[...]</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <pb n="TYI2071" facs="https://farm2.staticflickr.com/1742/40668617730_1d75c894e3_k_d.jpg"/>
            <div n="7" type="issue">
               <head type="main">"The Young Idea"</head>
               <head type="main">Chesapeake Chronicle and Weekly Journal</head>
               <head type="sub">Saturday 26 February 1859</head>
               <head type="sub">Vol 2. No 7.</head>
               <div type="article">
                  <head>No Title</head>
                  <p>Our readers will hardly require an excuse for the nonappearance of our Weekly Journal, on the last three Saturdays, (alas' it is
                     now weekly only in name) for all must have felt how monotonously the past-three or four weeks have flet: - unchequered by a
                     single occurrence of note, unmarked by a single episode, wehreby they may be remembered;- productive of naught to interest,
                     amuse, or cheer on such a stagnant state of affairs no wonder that ideas become tainted with dulness and that imaginiation is
                     entirely at a loss to provide amusement.</p>
                  <p>But we cannot let this, our last week at Jeddah pass, without commemorating our release from its influence wihtout hailing our
                     approaching departure, without rendering our last days more cheery by the production of a "Young Idea." Four Months have rolled
                     past quickly beholding us lying inactively in these <pb n="TYI2072"
                        facs="https://farm2.staticflickr.com/1731/27606329307_09ac843bfd_k_d.jpg"/>waters; our anchors rusting in their coral beds,
                     and our minds rusting in the no less corroding bed of sluggish, unvarying, inaction .The change already commences to exercise its
                     beneficial effects, faces begin to brighten, minds begin to expand at the thoughts of the rocky steeps of Aden, of again
                     careering swiftly over the bright waters of the Arabian Sea, of the pleasant verdure of Point de Galle, of the probably
                     occurrences of the next two months.</p>
                  <p>Farewell! then to Jeddah, farewell! to its distant hills, its sandy shores, its glistening walls, and crowded bazaarss; farewell
                     to its deep blue waters, and coral reefs, farewell to its desert borne breezes, adn san ladet atmostphere, adn with us our
                     readers all gladly echo "Farewell"!!!</p>
               </div>
               <div type="letter">
                  <head>The "Great Eastern" Steamship &amp; the Future of Trincomalie</head>
                  <p>[...]<pb n="TYI2073"/>[...]</p>
               </div>
               <div type="article">
                  <head>Notes about Jeddah</head>
                  <p>[...very interesting anecdotes about a visit ashore!]<pb n="TYI2074"/></p>
               </div>
               <div type="enigma">
                  <head>Historical Enigma</head>
                  <p>[...]</p>
               </div>
               <div type="naval_intelligence">
                  <head>Naval Intelligence</head>
                  <p>[...]</p>
               </div>
               <div type="epitome">
                  <head>Epitome.</head>
                  <p>[...]</p>
               </div>
               <div type="promotionsandappointments">
                  <head>Promotions &amp; Appointments</head>
                  <p>[...]8th <persName ref="#A_D_McArthur">Mr A.D. McArthur</persName> Clerk having passed provisionally before Mr Hayward Paymaster
                     to be Act Asst Paymr[...]</p>
               </div>
               <div type="charade">
                  <head>The Sailor's Charade.</head>
                  <p>[...]</p>
               </div>
               <div type="answer">
                  <head>Answer to REbus in No 6. Pomegranate</head>
                  <p>[...]</p>
               </div>
               <div type="publication_info">
                  <head>-</head>
                  <p>[...]</p>
               </div>
               <div type="-">
                  <head>-</head>
                  <p>[...]</p>
               </div>
               <div type="-">
                  <head>-</head>
                  <p>[...]</p>
               </div>
               <div type="-">
                  <head>-</head>
                  <p>[...]</p>
               </div>
               <div type="-">
                  <head>-</head>
                  <p>[...]</p>
               </div>
               <div type="-">
                  <head>-</head>
                  <p>[...]</p>
               </div>

            </div>
         </div>


      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
