<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title level="m" type="main">The Young Idea in Jeddah</title>
            <author>A.D. McArthur</author>
            <editor>Mary Isbell</editor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcription, encoding, and notes</resp>
               <name xml:id="initials">Mary Isbell</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>2018</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>TAPAS</publisher>
            <date>2018</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International License. </p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <monogr>
                  <editor>A.D. McArthur</editor>
                  <title>The Young Idea: A Naval Journal Edited on Board the H.M.S. Chesapeake in 1857, 1858 &amp; 1859 </title>
                  <idno type="callno">Edition created from copy in editor's private collection, only other known copy held at British Library:
                     1757.a.20/</idno>
                  <imprint>
                     <date>1867</date>
                     <biblScope>
                        <!-- type="pubPlace" -->
                        <ref type="address">170 Fleet Street, London, England</ref>
                        <name type="publisher">Paul Jerrard &amp; Son</name>
                     </biblScope>
                     <note type="project">outline of issues published off the coast of Jeddah</note>
                  </imprint>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>column breaks have not been retained, superscript has not been retained. Individual paragraphs have not been captured, making it seem
               like an entire contribution is one complete paragraph, which is not the case. Only the beginning of the contribution has been
               transcribed, followed by [...] indicating additional content to be transcribed.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <pb n="IMG_0286" facs="https://farm2.staticflickr.com/1740/40668620790_f4ce895caa_k_d.jpg"/>
         <div n="42" type="issue">
            <head type="main">"The Young Idea"</head>
            <head type="main">Chesapeake Chronicle and Weekly Journal</head>
            <head type="sub">Saturday 20th November 1858</head>
            <head type="sub">Vol 1. No 42</head>
            <div type="article">
               <p> Our stay at Jeddah has worn a very monotonous aspect. Strangers, to the shore, we have only been able to gaze from our bulwarks on
                  the far spreading sands, and barren hills of Arabia, and sigh to don the garment of some Mecca pilgrim, mount on the hump of some
                  fleet camel, and all Christian as we are, penetrate into the holiest shrines, and sanctuaries of Islam. [...]<pb n="TYI1422"/>[...]
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="article">
               <head>Sailing up the Red Sea.</head>
               <p>Sunday Morning 17 Octr. Having sailed with a fair breeze from Aden yesterday afternoon, we are this morning in sight of the straits
                  of Babel-Mandel. [...details the ship approaching Jeddah with the help of a Arab pilot named Abdullah...] <pb n="TYI1423"/>[...]</p>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <head>Tuesday 19 Octr 1858</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>The sun had past his highest point, the sea was calm &amp; bright</l>
                  <l>The ship was slowly urged along, by breezes soft and light</l>
                  <l>[...9 quatrains of verse describing a shark eating a midshipman's jacket and then being caught and eaten by the crew]</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="article">
               <head>The Late Comet.</head>
               <p>We are sorry that the very brief notes taken by "our own Observer", will not permit us to give any elaborate or scientific account
                  of this beautiful heavenly visitor. It was on teh Evening of Septr 30th after dropping anchor at Aden, that our attention was first
                  called to see teh bright stranger, which had made its appearance, unpredicted, &amp; unannounced among the celestial bodies of the
                  Northern Hemisphere.[...]<pb n="TYI1424"/>[...]</p>
            </div>
            <div type="Naval_Intelligence">
               <head>Naval Intelligence</head>
               <p>22nd Octr. H.M.S. Chesapeake arrived at Jeddah on Friday 22nd at 5 P.M. having been piloted in through the outer reefs by Mr Mayes
                  Master of the Cyclops. [...]</p>
            </div>
            <div type="Epitome">
               <head>Epitome</head>
               <p>On Monday Oct 25 preparations were made for the reception of His Excellency Nemuk Pacha, and the English &amp; French Commissioners,
                  but his Excellency being indiscposed after visiting the "Pelorus" was unable to visit us. The Commissioners however came on board
                  and inspected the ship.[...general reports of storms and boredom]</p>
            </div>
            <div type="Facetiae">
               <head>Facetiae</head>
               <p>A shocking punster, hearing that Jeddah was celebrated for Turquoise, said that if Turks &amp; Arabs were on unfriendly terms, no
                  doubt plenty of "Turk Wars" would be the result. [...other puns]</p>
            </div>
            <div type="Enigma">
               <head>Enigma</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>Bone on the wing of yon dark plumag'd bird</l>
                  <l>High o'er the earth how oft I took my flight:[...three quatrains of a riddle]</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="Answer_Rebus">
               <head/>
               <lg>
                  <l>!Tis the Emerald Isle where the rough jaunting "car".</l>
                  <l>Will bear you in country or town [in verse explaining that the answer is "carnation"]</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="Publication_Information">
               <head>The Young Idea</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>Published at the office No 1 POrt St Chesapeake, every Saturday[...]</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
         </div>
         <pb n="TYI1431"/>
         <div n="43" type="issue">
            <head type="main">"The Young Idea"</head>
            <head type="main">Chesapeake Chronicle and Weekly Journal</head>
            <head type="sub">Saturday 27th November 1858</head>
            <head type="sub">Vol 1. No 43</head>
            <div type="article">
               <p>Our past week has produced one circumstance which had caused some little excitement amongst the squadron, and has for a short period
                  dispeled the monotony of our life; we refer to the race between our Barge and the "Pelorus's" Cutter.[...]<pb n="TYI1432"/>[...]</p>
               <div type="article">
                  <head>Jeddah, our Visit to Namik Pacha.</head>
                  <head type="sub">Tuesday 26 Octr 1858</head>
                  <p>We left our ship, a large party of us, in three Boats at half past 8 a.m., and after various difficulties in avoiding coral
                     rocks, and crossing shoal Water, came alongside teh Jetty near the Southern extremity of teh Town. Here we perceived the
                     KaimaKhan, or Governor of Jeddah dressed in purple uniform coat, and attended by teh Harbour Master in his suit of brown cloth,
                     waiting to receive us. He shook each one by teh hand as we ascended the steps &amp; Passing under the gateway, found a number of
                     Arab steeds in gay trappings, &amp; saddles, ready for us to mount. We formed a brilliant cavalcade, as we set out on our
                     progress thro' the town. We were 20 in all, and all attired in our uniform frock coats &amp; swords with white flowing turbans
                     encircling our caps. Captains Pullen, and Parkin led teh way, attended by teh Kaima Khan, while we followed by twos and threes,
                     and well armed Turkish attendants, Bashi Bazouks we believe with plenty of silver mounted pistols at their girdles welked at our
                     horses heads. After passing an open space in which loungers were sitting smoking hookahs, and drinking coffee, &amp; camels lying
                     wiht piles of goods around them, our road lay thro' the long winding streets of the Bazaars, where articles of every description
                     were exposed for Sale, &amp; human faces of every shape and color met the view. There was so much novelty to attract the eye;
                     that it was difficult to notice anything occurately. The Bazaars were so narrow that two horsemen could with difficulty ride
                     abreast, without pushing against the wares on either side. In some parts swarms of flies rendered our progress annoying. There
                     were broad vessels piled up with dates, or melons, or pomegranates, or oranges; trays on which large broad cakes, or other
                     eatables were exposed for sale. shops in which the porous water coolers, and other simple earthenwares were hangingin, or silks
                     and muslins of various kinds, or strings of breads, amber black or white coral or cornelian, such as devout Musselmen use in
                     prayer, or Turkish slippers; or long pipes and outhpieces; all whihc for a moment only caught the eye as our steeds passed on.
                     The human faces most attracted us, the light hughed caucasian features of the Turk., the well bronzed countenance of teh native
                     Arab the broad Ethiopian visage of teh black slave, teh veiled face of some female, <choice>
                        <orig>here</orig>
                        <corr>her</corr>
                     </choice> eyes only peering thro' the white muslin "yek-mesh", the scowling gaze of the wild Bedouin as he stood erect in his
                     uncleanly brown robe, his head enveloped in a cowl, with his hand ready at the [...interesting exchange about tobacco as snuff,
                     with Pasha saying it was "good for the gums" and his inquiries about the men in black, who it turns out where the chaplains,
                     described by Parkin as "the two professors who instructed teh youths in theology &amp; navigation"...will continue in next
                     number]</p>
               </div>
               <div type="sporting_intelligence">
                  <head type="main">SPORTING INTELLIGENCE</head>
                  <head type="sub">Boat Race between the Chesapeakes Barge and Pelorus's Cutter.></head>
                  <p>[...]</p>
               </div>
               <div type="song">
                  <head type="main">(Song)</head>
                  <head type="main">The Cheasapeake's Barge</head>
                  <head type="sub">Air (Yankee doodle)</head>
                  <lg>
                     <l>of the "Chesapeake's of old,</l>
                     <l>[...]</l>
                     <pb n="?????"/>
                  </lg>
               </div>
               <div type="Article">
                  <head>Namik Pacha, &amp; the Merchants of Jeddah</head>
                  <p>It is said that Namik Pacha being fearful that the rich Merchants of Jeddah would remove their wealth at the sight of our English
                     ships, invited them to a friendly entertainment, and in true Eastern spirit then detained them in safe custody. eleven in number.
                     We hear also that the new Sheriff has in a similar way detained several at Mecca, with the view of procuring from them the fine
                     which is supposed will be exacted by the English and French Governments</p>
               </div>
               <div type="Epitome">
                  <head type="main">Epitome</head>
                  <head type="sub">Festivities in the Ward room.</head>
                  <p>On Wednesday Evening 25th Inst several officers from "Cyclops" and "Pelorus" assembled on board the "Chesapeake" and after much
                     merry dancing while teh Band was playing on the Main Deck, retired to teh Ward room to finish the Evening with a bowl of punch,
                     and a few concomitant songs [more details about celebrations and such...]</p>
               </div>
               <div> </div>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
