<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title><!-- The title of the project here. --></title>
            <editor role="Editor-in-Chief">Mary Isbell</editor>
            <editor role="Managing_Editor">Anna Kroon</editor>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>TBD</publisher>
            <pubPlace>TBD</pubPlace>
            <date>TBD</date>
         </publicationStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note><!-- Context for the extracted text. Format is dependent on the text. Example: Outline of issues and article titles from a newspaper. --></note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <monogr>
                  <!-- ?????? We need to find a tag that is the equivalent of imprint, but for manuscript items and even for published items, I'd like to include the library that holds the item-->
                  <author><!-- The author of the source text. --></author>
                  <title><!-- The title of the source text. --></title>
                  <imprint>
                     <publisher><!-- The publisher of the source text. --></publisher>
                     <pubPlace><!-- The place of publication for the source text. This may be 'born digital'. --></pubPlace>
                     <date><!-- The date of publication for the source text. --></date>
                  </imprint>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <!-- The tags and content within this element will be determined by the Editor-In-Cheif. -->
            <segmentation>
               <!-- This will be determined by the Editor-In-Chief. -->
               <p>here is a description of how divs work for this text</p>
            </segmentation>
            <correction>
               <!-- This will be determined by the Editor-In-Chief. -->
               <p>we corrected spelling and indicated as much</p>
            </correction>
            <normalization>
               <!-- This will be determined by the Editor-In-Chief. -->
               <p>we normalized and indicated as much</p>
            </normalization>
         </editorialDecl>

      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <!-- This will be determined by the Editor-In-Chief. -->
         <abstract>
            <p>Context for the extracted text. This will indlude historical information and information about the text as a whole. Format is dependent
               on the text. Example: Outline of issues and article titles from a newspaper.</p>
         </abstract>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>See versions of this file at the <ref target="https://github.com/MaryIsbell/ShipboardTheatricals">GitHub</ref> for this
            project.</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <head>Events of the Month of February.</head>
         <p>The close of February and the first week of March 1851, are replete with interest, and mark a fresh epoch in the fast changing history of
            our eventful sojourn in the Northern Regions</p>
         <pb/>
         <p>The arrival of the Sun in our heavens, was we may say commemorated by the Fancy Dress Ball_ of it we have elsewhere spoken. Hardly had our
            daylight extende itself to the length of ten hours, when <persName>M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Hamilton</persName> &amp; <persName>D<hi
                  rend="superscript">r</hi> Bradford</persName> with a Sledge, &amp; a party of Seamen, performed a pedestrian feat by walking to the Expeditions.<figure>
               <caption>Scene from the Pantomime of 'Zero'</caption>
            </figure> wintering under Cornwallis Island, and we rejoiced ot see them returned with some of our gallant friends who kindly came over to
            pay us a visit, &amp; merriment in their little Society as well as our own.</p>
         <p>The 'Assistance' had made arrangements to celebrate the anniversary of our Expedition having been put into commission by a performance on
            the boards of the Royal Arctic Theatre, unhappily a very severe gale of wind prevented this thier intention, being carried into effect,
            and the performance as well as the closing of the Theatre was unavoidably postponed to the 4<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> of March.</p>
         <p>On that Evening a crowded house proved how unabated was the interest fled in a Stage which has been a source of great amusement throughout
            the Squadron<cb/><figure>
               <caption>Scene from Charles XII.</caption>
            </figure></p>
         <p>Not small are the obligations which the non performers labour under to the many individuals who have in such divers
            <!-- This can't be the right word -->manners tended to the general amusement. Managers, Actors, Painters, Prompters, and Scene Shifters,
            <!-- etc etc --></p>
         <p>"Nobly each &amp; all their means have used" as the neat Epilogue truthfully says_ ans the result has been a Theatre unequalled in
            excellence by any Squadron, &amp; reflecting no small credit on the 'Assistances' in general_ especially when it be remembered that the
            performances have taken place on the Upper Deck with the external temperature as low as 30° below zero.</p>
         <p>The Original Pantomime of Zero, was again performed, and had been evidently much improved. A new Song or two was introduced &amp; the
            indefatigable <persName>M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Dean</persName> astonished the Audience by his clever imitation of a Bear &amp; a
            Fox.</p>
         <p>A witty &amp; highly diverting explanation of the figures exhibited by a Magic Lanthorn next followed in rapid succession and as the
            Family Herald would say "we were constantly thrown into a sweet agony of joy &amp; sorrow," by the sudden transition from the burning of
            Hindov Widows, to the bombardment of Jean d'Acre.</p>
         <pb/>
         <p>The pretty drama of Charles the 12<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> with the following Cast of Characters:_ <castList>
               <castItem>
                  <lb/><role>Charles XII,</role>___<actor><persName>L<hi rend="superscript">t</hi> Mecham.</persName></actor>
               </castItem>
               <castItem><lb/><role>Major Vauberg,</role>___<actor><persName>Capt<hi rend="superscript">n</hi> Ommanney</persName></actor></castItem>
               <castItem><lb/><role>Adam Brock,</role>___<actor><persName>M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Ede</persName></actor></castItem>
               <castItem><lb/><role>Triptolemus Muddlewerk,</role>___<actor><persName>M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>
                  Krabbe</persName></actor></castItem>
               <castItem><lb/><role>Gustavus de Mervelt,</role>___<actor><persName>M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>
                  Markham</persName></actor></castItem>
               <castItem><lb/><role>Colonel Reichil,</role>___<actor><persName>M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> May</persName></actor></castItem>
               <castItem><lb/><role>General Duckerst,</role>___<actor><persName>L<hi rend="superscript">t</hi> Cator</persName></actor></castItem>
               <castItem><lb/><role>Officers,</role>___<actor><persName>Mess<hi rend="superscript">re</hi>
                        Richards</persName></actor>&amp;<actor><persName>Shellabeer</persName></actor></castItem>
               <lb/>
               <castGroup rend="braced">
                  <roleDesc>Women</roleDesc>
                  <castItem><role>Eudiga</role>___<actor>M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> M<hi rend="superscript">c</hi>Dougall</actor></castItem>
                  <lb/>
                  <castItem><role>Ulrica</role>___<actor>M<hi rend="superscript"> Pearse</hi></actor></castItem>
               </castGroup>

            </castList>
            <lb/>closed the Evening's entertainment._ From the Royal Swede to the Officer of the Guard, all the parts were admirably sustained. Adam
            Brock was as like as the original as the imagination could picture it, and the worthy Burgomaster kept the Company in roard of laughter._
            Firman looked the picture of conscious innocence, and appeared fully alive to the fact that altho innocent, he might yet be drawn &amp;
            quartered for Royal pleasure or Stage effect.</p>
         <p>Oh!for a Crowgwill to tell of the facinating performance of Eudiga &amp; Ulrica. England's fiar daughters would have seen the truthful
            representationof the loves of Ulrica &amp; Gustavus de Mervelt, or Eudiga &amp; Coln<hi rend="superscript">l</hi> Richel.</p>
         <p>Where the young ladies could possibly have aquired the subtle knowledge they displayed in the woeful intricacy of female attire, we know
            not, suffice it, that not a <hi rend="underline">point</hi> was missing._ As a finale the Manager delivered, <lb/><hi>The following
               Epilouge, <lb/>from the pen of M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Ede._</hi>
            <lg>
               <l>When first this Curtain rose, we strove to say,</l>
               <l>All our sucess in your applause would lay.</l>
               <l>Thus trusting we have tried, &amp; not in vain,</l>
               <l>To hear your laughter o'er &amp; o'er again.</l>
               <l>One sole regret we had, until to night,</l>
               <cb/>
               <l>That those so near, could not with us unite;</l>
               <l>And in this mimic world, the hourse beguile,</l>
               <l>Where all must feel the want od woman's smile.</l>
               <l>But now 'tis o'er, the flow'r of day expands,</l>
               <l>And greedy time new sacrifice demands.</l>
               <l>The strength of youth, the wisdom of the sage.</l>
               <l>Must soon appear upon life's boundless stage.</l>
               <l>Amusement then to duty will give place,</l>
               <l>And lines of thought will mark the anxious face,</l>
               <l>In merriment &amp; fun we've joinged together,</l>
               <l>Defying coul &amp; every change of weather.</l>
               <l>Nobly each and all their means have used,</l>
               <l>First the Amusers, then in turn the Amused,</l>
               <l>In health &amp; happiness the time has fled;</l>
               <l>And bright success on all, its rays has shed.</l>
               <l>That our next efforts may as well succeed,</l>
               <l>Is the great wish in which we're all agreed.</l>
            </lg></p>
         <p>The Curtain then dropped amidst the loud cheets of a delighted audience, and thus concluded the performacnes of the Royal Arctic Theatre.
            A supper &amp; Refereshment, were as usual hospitably provide by the 'Jolly Assistances', to which right good justice was done by <figure>
               <caption>Scene from Charles XII.</caption>
            </figure>Midnight the time consuming gaities of out Arctic Winter had passed away and we rose on the morrow, to look forward and prepare
            for the great &amp; glorious labour before us.</p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
