<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title level="m" type="main">The Young Idea in Jeddah</title>
            <author>A.D. McArthur</author>
            <editor>Mary Isbell</editor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcription, encoding, and notes</resp>
               <name xml:id="initials">Mary Isbell</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>2018</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>TAPAS</publisher>
            <date>2018</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International License. </p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <monogr>
                  <editor>A.D. McArthur</editor>
                  <title>The Young Idea: A Naval Journal Edited on Board the H.M.S. Chesapeake in 1857, 1858 &amp; 1859 </title>
                  <idno type="callno">Edition created from copy in editor's private collection, only other known copy held at British Library:
                     1757.a.20/</idno>
                  <imprint>
                     <date>1867</date>
                     <biblScope>
                        <!-- type="pubPlace" -->
                        <ref type="address">170 Fleet Street, London, England</ref>
                        <name type="publisher">Paul Jerrard &amp; Son</name>
                     </biblScope>
                     <note type="project">outline of issues published off the coast of Jeddah</note>
                  </imprint>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <particDesc>
            <listPerson>
               <person xml:id="A_D_McArthur">
                  <note>Alexander D. McArthur, a clerk, joined the Chesapeake on December 9th 1857. He was born on December 25th 1835 in Woolwich,
                     Kent, making him 21 when he came aboard. Census records for the town of Woolwich in 1851 reveal the family of John McAurthur, a
                     captain in the Royal Marines, who lived with his wife Mary E., a son James (a gentleman, aged 29), a son John (no occupation,
                     aged 27), a son Henry (a clerk in the wine trade, aged 17), a son Alexander D (a scholar, aged 15), a son Hanibal (no occupation,
                     aged 13), and a servant Esther Johnson (aged 20).</note>
                  <!--<bibl><<msIdentifier><msName>Muster Book of Her Majesty's Ship Chesapeake Commencing 1st January 1858 Ending 31st March 1858</msName>
                        <institution>National Archives at Kew</institution>
                     <idno>ADM 38/2884</idno>
                     </msIdentifier></bibl>
                  <bibl>
                  <bibl><msIdentifier><msName>Census Returns of England and Wales, 1851. Kew, Surrey, England</msName><institution>The National Archives of the
                     UK (TNA): Public Record Office (PRO)</institution>                       
                     </msIdentifier></bibl>-->
               </person>
               <person>
                  <persName xml:id="J_W_L_Bampfield">John William Lewis Bampfield</persName>
                  <note>Reverend John William Lewis Bampfield joined the Chesapeake on July 24th 1857 and was a regular contributor to and supporter
                     of The Young Idea. While his age is not recorded in the muster book, census records reveal that Bampfield was born in June of
                     1823, so he was in his mid-thirties during the cruise. He was commissioned as chaplain aboard a different royal naval vessel in
                     Port Royal, Jamaica before his arrival aboard the Chesapeake. His detailed journal provides an additional witness to The Young
                     Idea, providing fascinating points of contrast from the facsimile edition that McArthur had printed in 1867 and offering hints
                     about the authorship of contributions through his inclusion of the initials of authors (a marked list). </note>
               </person>
               <person>
                  <persName xml:id="Edgell">Harry Edmund Edgell</persName>
                  <note>Harry Edmund Edgell joined the Chesapeake as Commodore after the period chronicled in the issues included in this edition. He
                     was an enthusiastic supporter of The Young Idea. In <hi rend="italics">Martello Tower" in China, and the Pacific in H.M.S.
                        "Tribune," 1856-60</hi>, Francis Martin Norman recounts Edgell's enthusiastic support for a shipboard theatrical aboard H.M.S.
                     Tribune in 1857, when he was captain of the ship. Edgell composed the prologue for the play and painted the drop-scene (50). The
                     National Maritime Museum at Greenwich (NMM) holds over 300 watercolors by Edgell, including some undertaken during the cruise
                     chronicled in The Young Idea. The NMM's biographical note on Edgell reads as follows: "Edgell was promoted to lieutenant in 1828,
                     to commander in 1837 and to captain in 1846. He was appointed to command the Tribune in 1855 when she was in the Crimea. During
                     this commission she went to the Pacific and finally to China. In 1857 Edgell was the Senior Naval Officer at Hong Kong and he
                     transferred into the Bittern tender commanding the gun boats on the Canton River during the hostilities with the Chinese. In 1858
                     be was given command of the squadron in Indian waters, during which time he commanded the Chesapeake and later the Retribution.
                     The latter returned to England and was paid off in 1860. Edgell had no further active employment and was promoted on the retired
                     list, reaching the rank of vice-admiral in 1871."</note>
               </person>
               <person>
                  <persName xml:id="Watson">Commodore Rundle Burges Watson</persName>
                  <note>Excerpts from “Watson, Rundle Burges” by <bibl><author>by J.K. Laughton, rev. Andrew Lambert</author></bibl> for the
                           <bibl><title>Oxford Dictionary of National Biography</title></bibl>: <quote>"Watson, Rundle Burges (1809–1860), naval
                        officer, was the eldest son of Captain Joshua Rowley Watson (1772–1810). He entered the navy in November 1821, and was
                        promoted lieutenant on 7 October 1829. [...] On 23 December 1842 he was advanced to post rank, and on 24 December was made a
                        CB. [...] In December 1852 [Watson] was appointed to the new steam frigate Impérieuse (50 guns), then, and for some years
                        later, considered one of the finest ships in the navy. In 1854 she was sent into the Baltic in advance of the fleet, Watson
                        being senior officer of the squadron of small vessels appointed to watch the breaking up of the ice, and to see that no
                        Russian warships got to sea. It was an arduous service well performed. The Impérieuse continued with the flying squadron in
                        the Baltic during the campaigns of 1854 and 1855, and until the signing of peace in March 1856. As the senior officer of the
                        frigate squadron, and generally on detached service, Watson demonstrated the highest standards of seamanship, judgement, and
                        leadership. After the peace the Impérieuse was sent to the North American station; she returned to England and was paid off
                        early in 1857. From May 1856 until his death Watson was naval aide-de-camp to the queen. In June 1859 he was appointed
                        captain-superintendent of Sheerness Dockyard, where he died on 5 July 1860. An officer of great ability, Watson was one of the
                        last great sailing-ship captains, and the first frigate captain of the steam era."</quote></note>
               </person>
               <person>
                  <persName xml:id="Pratt">Archdeacon Pratt</persName>
                  <note>Excerpt from “Pratt, John Henry” by <bibl><author>Anita McConnell</author></bibl> for the <bibl><title>Oxford Dictionary of
                           National Biography</title></bibl>: <quote>“Pratt, John Henry (bap. 1809, d. 1871), Church of England clergyman and
                        mathematician, was baptized on 30 June 1809 at St Mary Woolnoth, London, one of two sons of Josiah Pratt (1768–1844), Church
                        of England clergyman, and his wife, Elizabeth, formerly Jowett. He was educated at Oakham School, Rutland, and entered
                        Gonville and Caius College, Cambridge, in 1829, graduating BA in 1833 as third wrangler. He was elected to a fellowship, and
                        proceeded MA in 1836. After taking orders he was appointed through the influence of Daniel Wilson, bishop of Calcutta, a
                        chaplain of the East India Company in 1838. He became Wilson's domestic chaplain and in 1850 archdeacon of
                     Calcutta.”</quote></note>
               </person>
               <person>
                  <persName xml:id="George_Horner">George Horner</persName>
                  <note>George Horner, a bandsman, joined the Chesapeake on August 12, 1857. He was born in London in 1817. The muster book for the
                     Chesapeake claims to offer the first entry for George Horner, perhaps meaning this was his first time at sea.<bibl>Muster Book of
                        Her Majesty's Ship Chesapeake Commencing 1st January 1858 Ending 31st March 1858, held by the National Archives at Kew (ADM
                        38/2884)</bibl></note>
               </person>
               <person>
                  <persName xml:id="Charles_Stewart">Charles Stewart</persName>
                  <note>Charles Stewart, an ordinary seaman, joined the Chesapeake on May 23, 1857. He was born in London and served aboard HMS
                     Gladiator just before joining the Chesapeake. He was born in 1834.<bibl>Muster Book of Her Majesty's Ship Chesapeake Commencing
                        1st January 1858 Ending 31st March 1858, held by the National Archives at Kew (ADM 38/2884)</bibl></note>
               </person>
               <person>
                  <persName xml:id="Thomas_Walsh">Thomas Walsh</persName>
                  <note>Thomas Walsh, an ordinary seaman, joined the Chesapeake on August 15, 1857. He was born in London in 1834 and served aboard
                     HMS Cressy just before joining the Chesapeake.<bibl>Muster Book of Her Majesty's Ship Chesapeake Commencing 1st January 1858
                        Ending 31st March 1858, held by the National Archives at Kew (ADM 38/2884)</bibl></note>
               </person>
               <person>
                  <persName xml:id="Robert_Wilkinson">Robert Wilkinson</persName>
                  <note>Robert Wilkinson, a private in the Royal Marines, joined the Chesapeake on July 25th 1857. He was born in Sitchfield,
                        Staffordshire.<bibl>Muster Book of Her Majesty's Ship Chesapeake Commencing 1st January 1858 Ending 31st March 1858, held by
                        the National Archives at Kew (ADM 38/2884)</bibl></note>
               </person>
               <person>
                  <persName xml:id="Henry_Underhill">Henry Underhill</persName>
                  <note>muster#153, ordinary seaman from Alesford, 36 when coming aboard the Chesapeake<bibl>Muster Book of Her Majesty's Ship
                        Chesapeake Commencing 1st January 1858 Ending 31st March 1858, held by the National Archives at Kew (ADM 38/2884)</bibl>
                  </note>
               </person>
               <person>
                  <persName xml:id="John_Welsh">John Welsh</persName>
                  <note>John Welsh, an ordinary seaman, joined the Chesapeake on February 20, 1857. He was born in Mayo<bibl>Muster Book of Her
                        Majesty's Ship Chesapeake Commencing 1st January 1858 Ending 31st March 1858, held by the National Archives at Kew (ADM
                        38/2884)</bibl></note>
               </person>
               <person>
                  <persName xml:id="Henry_Montagu">Henry Montagu</persName>
                  <note>Henry Montagu, yeoman of signals, joined the Chesapeake on July 28, 1857 after serving aboard HMS President. He was born in
                     St. Hilliers, Jersey (the Channel Islands) in 1826, making him 32 at the time of the performance.<bibl>Muster Book of Her
                        Majesty's Ship Chesapeake Commencing 1st January 1858 Ending 31st March 1858, held by the National Archives at Kew (ADM
                        38/2884)</bibl></note>
               </person>
               <person>
                  <persName xml:id="Isaac_Wright">Isaac Wright</persName>
                  <note>Isaac Wright, an ordinary sailor 2nd class, joined the Chesapeake on September 4th 1857. Hew as born in Sunderland in 1835,
                     making him 23 at the time of the performance.<bibl>Muster Book of Her Majesty's Ship Chesapeake Commencing 1st January 1858
                        Ending 31st March 1858, held by the National Archives at Kew (ADM 38/2884)</bibl></note>
               </person>
               <person>
                  <persName xml:id="Henry_Hamilton">Henry Hamilton</persName>
                  <note>C. R. B. Hamilton (the only Hamilton in the musters) was a naval cadet who served aboard <orgName ref="Colossus">HMS
                        Colossus</orgName> before joining the Chesapeake on July 23, 1857. He was born in County Tyrone, Ireland in December of 1842,
                     making him 15 at the time the performance<bibl>Muster Book of Her Majesty's Ship Chesapeake Commencing 1st January 1858 Ending
                        31st March 1858, held by the National Archives at Kew (ADM 38/2884)</bibl></note>
               </person>
               <person>
                  <persName xml:id="James_Brown">James Browne</persName>
                  <note>James Brown, an ordinary seaman, joined the Chesapeake on July 23, 1857, after serving aboard <orgName ref="Cuckoo">HMS
                        Cuckoo</orgName> until February 3, 1857. He was born at Sheerness on the 17th of January 1829, making him 28 at the time of
                     the performance<bibl>Muster Book of Her Majesty's Ship Chesapeake Commencing 1st January 1858 Ending 31st March 1858, held by the
                        National Archives at Kew (ADM 38/2884)</bibl></note>
               </person>
               <person>
                  <persName xml:id="William_Connell">William T Connell</persName>
                  <note>William T. Connell, an ordinary seaman, joined the Chesapeake on July 31 1857, after serving aboard <orgName ref="Eurydice"
                        >HMS Eurydice</orgName> until 17 June 1857. He was born in London in 1835, making him 27 at the time of the
                        performance.<bibl>Muster Book of Her Majesty's Ship Chesapeake Commencing 1st January 1858 Ending 31st March 1858, held by the
                        National Archives at Kew (ADM 38/2884)</bibl></note>
               </person>
               <person>
                  <persName xml:id="Taylor">Edward Taylor</persName>
                  <note>Edward Taylor, Assistant Engineer 3rd class (a commissioned officer), joined the Chesapeake on July 25th 1857. His age was not
                     recorded in the muster book<bibl>Muster Book of Her Majesty's Ship Chesapeake Commencing 1st January 1858 Ending 31st March 1858,
                        held by the National Archives at Kew (ADM 38/2884)</bibl></note>
               </person>
               <person>
                  <persName xml:id="Brownrigg">Charles J. Brownrigg</persName>
                  <note>Charles J. Brownrigg, a mate (a commissioned officer), joined the Chesapeake on August 4th, 1857. His age was not recorded in
                     the muster book.<bibl>Muster Book of Her Majesty's Ship Chesapeake Commencing 1st January 1858 Ending 31st March 1858, held by
                        the National Archives at Kew (ADM 38/2884)</bibl></note>
               </person>
               <person>
                  <persName xml:id="Wilkinson">Wilkinson</persName>
                  <note>Mr. Wilkinson, a clerk (a subordinate officer), joined the Chesapeake on July 23rd 1857 after serving aboard HMS Majestic. He
                     was born in Suffolk in 1836, which would make him 22 at the time of the cricket match in Calcutta<bibl>Muster Book of Her
                        Majesty's Ship Chesapeake Commencing 1st January 1858 Ending 31st March 1858, held by the National Archives at Kew (ADM
                        38/2884)</bibl></note>
               </person>
               <person>
                  <persName xml:id="Shortt">John Shortt</persName>
                  <note>John Shortt, a subordinate officer, joined the Chesapeake on July 23rd 1857, after serving aboard HMS Euridice. He was born in
                     Bombay in 1838, making him 20 at the time of this cricket match in Calcutta.<bibl>Muster Book of Her Majesty's Ship Chesapeake
                        Commencing 1st January 1858 Ending 31st March 1858, held by the National Archives at Kew (ADM 38/2884)</bibl></note>
               </person>
               <person>
                  <persName xml:id="Reynolds">S. Reynolds</persName>
                  <note>S. Reynolds, an ordinary seaman, joined the Chesapeake on September 4th 1857. He was born in Landport (Portsmouth) in 1839,
                     making him 19 at the time of the cricket match in Calcutta.<bibl>Muster Book of Her Majesty's Ship Chesapeake Commencing 1st
                        January 1858 Ending 31st March 1858, held by the National Archives at Kew (ADM 38/2884)</bibl></note>
               </person>
               <person>
                  <persName xml:id="Theobald">C.B. Theobald</persName>
                  <note>C.B. Theobald, a naval cadet, joined the Chesapeake on July 24th 1857. He was born in Mark's Tey, Essex in 1843, making him 15
                     at the time of the cricket match in Calcutta.<bibl>Muster Book of Her Majesty's Ship Chesapeake Commencing 1st January 1858
                        Ending 31st March 1858, held by the National Archives at Kew (ADM 38/2884)</bibl></note>
               </person>
               <person>
                  <persName xml:id="Cooper">Cooper</persName>
                  <note>There are three different members of the ship's company with the last name Cooper. The only thing we can tell about the
                     "Cooper" referenced in the cricket match is that he was not a commissioned officer, but an ordinary seaman.<bibl>Muster Book of
                        Her Majesty's Ship Chesapeake Commencing 1st January 1858 Ending 31st March 1858, held by the National Archives at Kew (ADM
                        38/2884)</bibl></note>
               </person>
               <person>
                  <persName xml:id="Chute">Charles T. Chute</persName>
                  <note>Charles T. Chute, a subordinate officer, joined the Chesapeake on July 23rd 1857, after serving aboard Euridice. He was born
                     in London in 1841, making him 17 at the time of the cricket match in Calcutta.<bibl>Muster Book of Her Majesty's Ship Chesapeake
                        Commencing 1st January 1858 Ending 31st March 1858, held by the National Archives at Kew (ADM 38/2884)</bibl></note>
               </person>
               <person>
                  <persName xml:id="Bew">James Bew</persName>
                  <note>James Bew, an experienced seaman, joined the Chesapeake on August 1st 1857. He was born in 1833, making him 25 at the time of
                     the cricket match in Calcutta.<bibl>Muster Book of Her Majesty's Ship Chesapeake Commencing 1st January 1858 Ending 31st March
                        1858, held by the National Archives at Kew (ADM 38/2884)</bibl></note>
               </person>
               <person>
                  <persName xml:id="Oxley">C.L. Oxley</persName>
                  <note>C.L. Oxley, a midshipman, joined the Chesapeake on July 29th 1857. He was born in 1841, making him 17 at the time of the
                     cricket match in Calcutta.<bibl>Muster Book of Her Majesty's Ship Chesapeake Commencing 1st January 1858 Ending 31st March 1858,
                        held by the National Archives at Kew (ADM 38/2884)</bibl></note>
               </person>
               <person>
                  <persName xml:id="Behadoor">Rajah Behadoor</persName>
                  <note>Still searching for biographical details on Rajah Behadoor</note>
               </person>
               <person>
                  <persName xml:id="Hope">Hope</persName>
                  <note>Hope played for the "squadron's eleven" and does not appear in Chesapeak muster book, which means he likely belonged to
                     another ship in the squadron<bibl>Muster Book of Her Majesty's Ship Chesapeake Commencing 1st January 1858 Ending 31st March
                        1858, held by the National Archives at Kew (ADM 38/2884)</bibl></note>
               </person>
               <person>
                  <persName xml:id="Haswell">Haswell</persName>
                  <note>Haswell served aboard Himalaya until he was injured and replaced by Piers.<bibl>Muster Book of Her Majesty's Ship Chesapeake
                        Commencing 1st January 1858 Ending 31st March 1858, held by the National Archives at Kew (ADM 38/2884)</bibl></note>
               </person>
               <person>
                  <persName xml:id="Kelly">Lieutenant Edward Kelly</persName>
                  <note>Lieutenant Edward Kelly does not appear in the muster book of HMS Chesapeake. <bibl>Muster Book of Her Majesty's Ship
                        Chesapeake Commencing 1st January 1858 Ending 31st March 1858, held by the National Archives at Kew (ADM
                     38/2884)</bibl></note>
               </person>
               <person>
                  <persName xml:id="Parkin">George H. Parkin</persName>
                  <note>George H. Parkin was named acting commander of HMS Chesapeake on February 1st 1858 and came aboard on February 25th after
                     serving aboard Roebuck. <bibl>Muster Book of Her Majesty's Ship Chesapeake Commencing 1st January 1858 Ending 31st March 1858,
                        held by the National Archives at Kew (ADM 38/2884)</bibl></note>
               </person>
               <person>
                  <persName xml:id="Piers">S.B. Piers</persName>
                  <note>S.B. Piers, a commander, joined the Chesapeake on July 28th 1857. He was discharged on January 22nd 1858 to serve aboard HMS
                     Himalaya when vice Haswell was invalided.<bibl>Muster Book of Her Majesty's Ship Chesapeake Commencing 1st January 1858 Ending
                        31st March 1858, held by the National Archives at Kew (ADM 38/2884)</bibl></note>
               </person>
               <person>
                  <persName xml:id="Namik_Pacha">Namik Pacha</persName>
                  <note>cite one of the articles on the uprising</note>
               </person>
            </listPerson>
            <listOrg>
               <org xml:id="Pelorus">
                  <note>HMS Pelorus was a Royal Navy screw corvette with twenty-one guns in the Pearl class. She was launched on February 5, 1858 and
                     her masting and fitting-out was completed on September 10, 1857. She was 200 feet long, 40 feet 4 inches at the broadest point,
                     with a depth in the hold of 23 feet 11 inches. As Lyon and Winfield explain, "Corvette designs were rapidly enlarged over the
                     1860s, as the corvette began to take over the traditional role of policing the high seas. To this end they were all built as
                     steam auxiliaries, designed to cruise under sail" (207). HMS Pelorus was broken up for parts at Devonport on February 3, 1869.
                     David Lyon and Rif Winfield, The Sail &amp; Steam Navy List: All the Ships of the Royal Navy, 1815–1889 (London: Chatham
                     Publishing), 2004.</note>
               </org>
               <org>
                  <orgName xml:id="Roebuck">Roebuck</orgName>
                  <note>HMS Roebuck was a Royal Navy despatch vessel with 5 guns in the Intrepid class. She was launched on March 22, 1856 and her
                     masting and fitting-out was completed on August 25, 1857. She was 200 feet long, 179 feet 5 1/4 inches at the broadest point,
                     with a depth in the hold of 14 feet 6 inches. She was built for a company of 100 men. As Lyon and Winfield explain, "The outbreak
                     of the Russian War demonstrated the need for numerous manoeuvrable, shallow-draught vessels for coastal and inshore operations in
                     the Baltic and Black Seas. Six small screw steamers of the Arrow Class were approved to be built by contract in the Thames [...]"
                     (218). The Roebuck was one of twenty additional vessels ordered in 1855 (218-219). David Lyon and Rif Winfield, The Sail &amp;
                     Steam Navy List: All the Ships of the Royal Navy, 1815–1889 (London: Chatham Publishing), 2004.</note>
               </org>
               <org>
                  <orgName xml:id="Cyclops">Cyclops</orgName>
                  <note>HMS Cyclops was a Royal Navy steam vessel with six guns in the Cyclops class. She was launched on July 10, 1839. She was 190
                     feet 3 inches long, 163 feet 6 inches at the broadest point, with a depth in the hold of 37 feet 6 inches. She was built for a
                     company of 175 to 200 men. As Lyon and Winfield explain, the ship was re-armed in 1856 "with 2x 68 pdrds (95cwt) on the pivots
                     and 4 x 10in (84cwt) on the broadside trucks." They also explain that she "was fitted 1856/57 to assist with the laying of the
                     Atlantic cable (151). David Lyon and Rif Winfield, The Sail &amp; Steam Navy List: All the Ships of the Royal Navy, 1815–1889
                     (London: Chatham Publishing), 2004. </note>
               </org>
               <org>
                  <orgName xml:id="Chesapeake">Chesapeake</orgName>
                  <note>HMS Chesapeake was a Royal Navy screw frigate with fifty-one guns in the Forte (or Imperieuse) class, which was one of several
                     classes including the thirty new wooden screw frigates completed between 1849 and 1865 (197). She was built in dry dock, launched
                     on September 7, 1855, and her masting and fitting-out was completed on August 28, 1857. She was 212 feet long, 50 feet 2 inches
                     at the broadest point, with a depth in the hold of 16 feet and 9 inches. She was built for a company of 515 men. The Chesapeake
                     was sold in 1867 to be broken up for parts at Charlton (200). David Lyon and Rif Winfield, The Sail &amp; Steam Navy List: All
                     the Ships of the Royal Navy, 1815–1889 (London: Chatham Publishing), 2004.</note>
               </org>
            </listOrg>
         </particDesc>
      </profileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>column breaks have not been retained, superscript has not been retained. Individual paragraphs have not been captured, making it seem
               like an entire contribution is one complete paragraph, which is not the case. Only the beginning of most contributions have been
               transcribed, followed by [...] indicating additional content to be transcribed. Where there is no title, "No Title" is used as the
               header.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>      
            <pb n="BETYI1341"/>
            <div n="34" type="issue">
               <head type="main">-</head>
               <head type="main">-</head>
               <head type="sub">-</head>
               <head type="sub">-</head>
               <div type="-">
                  <head>-</head>
                  <p>[...]</p>
               </div>
               <div type="-">
                  <head>-</head>
                  <p>[...]</p>
               </div>
               <div type="-">
                  <head>-</head>
                  <p>[...]</p></div>              
               <div type="play_review">
                  <head>????</head>
                  <p>On Friday Evening (28th Inst.) our Quarterdeck presented a gay scene, our Amateurs providing us with a first-rate Evening
                     amusement. The Guns being removed, the whole space of the Quarter deck was converted into a Saloon festooned with flags, &amp; <del>
                        <gap reason="illegible"/>
                     </del> decorated with beautiful flowers, and green boughs. Chandeliers, constructed with bayonets, hung from above, giving
                     abundance of light; the Capstan was taken away, &amp; its space occupied by a square ottoman; chairs &amp; benches filled the
                        <gap reason="illegible"/> portion of the Deck, while a succession of rising seats extending back to the bridge accommodated a
                     multitude of bluejacket spectators. This bridge alas being <del>itself</del>fully crowded. The stage itself was raised on the
                     Starboard side, between the Mainmast and the Gangway, about 4 feet above the Deck, the Orchestra being arranged in front. The
                     stage arrangements were very good, the lights well managed, and the scenery by Geo Horner, excellent. This being regarded as a
                     farewell entertainment from the Officers of the Chesapeake, our Ship was enlivened by the presence of most of the ladies and
                     gentlemen of Trincomalee, as well as a few of the passengers from the "Australasian", and officers as well as men, from the
                     "Pelorus", &amp; the Fort. The following were the cast of characters. [...]. The pieces chosen were well suited to develop the
                     various talents of the Actors:--Geo: Horner, as King Charles 2nd looked &amp; acted the "Merry Monarch" well, and Chas Stewart as
                     "Rochester" did no less well. But no doubt Capt Copp, the kind-hearted old Sailor (Thos Walshe) was the life and soul of the
                     piece, &amp; kept us in roars of laughter with his quaint sayings whenever he made his appearance. "Lady Clara" looked the lady
                     well, but spoke timidly, and "mary" alas required a little more confidence. In the 2nd Piece "Raising the Wind," the part of
                     "Jeremy Didler" was ably sustained by <gap reason="illegible"/> Wright, &amp; "Fainwould" the simple cockney was admirably
                     impersonated by Chs Stewart. Great credit is due also to Wm Connell for the way in which he played the lady's part of "Ship
                     Laurelia Durable": this appears to be his particular forte. Thos Walshe again shone as "Sam" the Yorkshire waiter and the minor
                     characters also did well. Seldome have we seen an audience so well pleased, our actors so well applauded. the "jig" by Thos
                     Walshe was as excellent as usual, &amp; the "Yo, heave oh!" sung by Wm Connell produced a pleasing effect by the Chorus it raised
                     from the Bluejackets present […]</p>
               </div>
            </div>
      
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
